<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A word of prophesy, concerning the Parliament, generall, and the army. With A little of the first Adam. Wherein are divers objections answered, concerning that position of God, being the author of sinne. / By Henry Pinnell.</title>
            <author>Pinnell, Henry.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1648</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 142 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 49 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A90716</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing P2280</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E1184_8</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R210114</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99868940</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99868940</idno>
            <idno type="VID">121297</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A90716)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 121297)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 251:E1184[8])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A word of prophesy, concerning the Parliament, generall, and the army. With A little of the first Adam. Wherein are divers objections answered, concerning that position of God, being the author of sinne. / By Henry Pinnell.</title>
                  <author>Pinnell, Henry.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[20], 74, [2] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for George Whittington and Giles Calvert, and are to be sold at the Blew Anchor neare the Royall Exchange in Cornhill,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1648]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Place and date of publication from Wing.</note>
                  <note>"A little of the first Adam, and how occasioned" has caption title.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Oct: 5 1648".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Civil War, 1642-1649 --  Prophecies --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:121297:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A WORD OF PROPHESY, CONCERNING <hi>The Parliament, Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall, and the Army.</hi> With <hi>A little of the First Adam.</hi> Wherein Are divers Objections anſwer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, concerning that poſition of God, being the Author of Sinne.</p>
            <p>By <hi>Henry Pinnell.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <p>Cry aloud, ſpare not, lift up thy Voyce like a Trumpet, and ſhew my people their tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſions, and the Houſe of Jacob their ſinnes,</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Eſ. 58.1.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <q>
               <p>I will get me unto the great men, and will ſpeake unto them,</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Jer. 5.5.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <q>
               <p>Thou ſhalt ſpeake my words unto them, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they will heare, or whether they will forbeare,</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Verſ. 7.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <q>
               <p>It is required in Stewards, that a man be found faithfull,</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>1 Cor. 4.2.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>Printed for <hi>George Whittington</hi> and <hi>Giles Calvert,</hi> and are to be ſold at the <hi>Blew Anchor</hi> neare the <hi>Royall Exchange</hi> in <hi>Cornhill.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:121297:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:121297:2"/>
            <head>To the Right Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipfull the Lady <hi>Anne Aston,</hi> elect and called of God, and therefore de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſed of the World, but honoured and beloved of all that are choſen and called out of it.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Madam,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>Onfuſion and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverſy, the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequence &amp; com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panion thereof, like two blacke clouds, cover the face and glory of this viſible Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            <p>The comfort and content, the heaven and happineſſe of the creature, is overſpread and hid
<pb facs="tcp:121297:3"/>with the thick vailes and ſhadowes of death and darkneſſe.</p>
            <p>What peace then, or proſperity is to be expected here,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſ.</hi> 119.96 <hi>Eccl.</hi> 1.2. <hi>Eſ.</hi> 23.9.</note> in the midſt of ſuch perplexities? Vanity and mortality is written upon all ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lunary and earthly perfections, and will ſtaine them. Increated light onely cannot be comprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded by darkneſſe. <hi>Joh.</hi> 1.5. Jeſus Chriſt in the ſpirit was ſeene by thoſe that were ſpirituall in the darkeſt times: We beheld his glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry (when the Jews and others ſaw onely his ſhame and (aſſumed) baſeneſſe) We ſaw it, as the glory of the onely begotten Son of the Father, <hi>v.</hi> 14.</p>
            <p>But when men waite for (crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted) light, behold obſcurity: when they looke for the brightneſſe (of the earthy and created ſtate) they walke in darkneſſe.</p>
            <p>The Sunne of this world goes downe into a night, yea, it ſets at noon-day, and the earth is dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in the cleare day: Did not <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam</hi> dye when he was riſen, and aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cended to the Meridian of his crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
<pb facs="tcp:121297:3"/>life? And did not, even then, the ſable cloud of death overſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow all the inhabitants of his Ioynes, and eclipſe all that Beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, ſplendour, glory, excellency and perfection of his created ſtate? You are therfore admoniſhed from the Lord [the Glory of whoſe ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty when it ariſeth, will terribly ſhake all earthly foundations, car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall confidence and fleſhly Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples] to ceaſe from man,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 2.7.</note> [from that man, that <hi>Adam</hi>] whoſe breath is in his noſtrils, as one not to bee accounted of. What reckoning ſhould you make of that duſt of the ground, that earthly <hi>Adam</hi> who hath (only) breath breathed (but) into his noſtrils? The earthy and fleſhly <hi>Microcoſme,</hi> or that little world, Man, with all that he hath, which is beneath heaven, which is not of an heavenly nature, ſhall be deſtroyed when the floud of the ſpirit is poured out upon all fleſh, though it hath the breath of life in it, the life of the firſt <hi>Adam,</hi> as once the old world was by the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luge of waters. No man (no not
<pb facs="tcp:121297:4"/>the firſt <hi>Adam</hi>) did ever aſcend to an heavenly ſtate: None but Jeſus Chriſt the ſecond <hi>Adam,</hi> this Son of man which came to earth from heaven,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Io.</hi> 3.13. <hi>Eph.</hi> 1.3. <hi>&amp;</hi> 2.6.</note> and was in heaven upon earth; He, and He onely aſcendeth to heaven, and raiſeth up thoſe that are in him to heavenly places, a condition, ſtate, righteouſneſſe truly heavenly. <hi>Adam</hi> had his root and riſe but in and from the earth; how then could his righteouſneſſe be heavenly or ſpirituall? as is the tree, ſuch is the fruit: Men do not expect grapes from thornes, nor figs from thiſtles. I never heard of any tree ſo tall, whoſe root was in the ground, and the toppe touched the skyes. The Tower that was in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended to be carried to that height,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 11.</note> could never be finiſhed: the work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men were ſcattered before the worke was perfected. How vile and void of underſtanding is vain man, to thinke to eſcape the vengeance of heaven, the foundation of whoſe ſecurity is laid in earth?</p>
            <p>And yet how are the childrens teeth of this generation ſet on edge
<pb facs="tcp:121297:4"/>with the ſowre grapes that their Fathers have eaten: bad preſidents in the parents are of miſchievous conſequence to their poſterity. <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam</hi> had but a <hi>terrene</hi> Paradiſe at beſt, yet by the fruit of knowledge therein he aſpired to an equality with God: and how doe his chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren ſtill banker and long after that earthy excellency of his? How do they ſtruggle and ſtrive to creep up unto that terreſtriall glory? How doe they hunger and thirſt af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter that goodly appearance of his ſpiritual &amp; heavenly know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, falſly ſo called, ſuppoſing it to be really and properly of a coe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſtiall and divine perfection? This is the (earthy) Mountaine that the Fathers have worſhipped in, and their children doe not yet know the way to <hi>Sion.</hi> Many there be that ſay, <hi>Wee will follow our Fathers;</hi> but few call to remembrance, how they have <hi>ſinned with their Fathers.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ier.</hi> 44.17. <hi>Pſ.</hi> 106.6.</note>
            </p>
            <p>The entrance, progreſſe and pat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terne of confuſion is laid downe, <hi>Gen.</hi> 11. and every generation of
<pb facs="tcp:121297:5"/>
               <hi>Adam</hi> takes up an exact imitati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</p>
            <p>For when men take their jour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney from the Eaſt, when they for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake the ſpring of light, the mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of the day, the Day-ſtar; that bright and Morning-ſtar, Jeſus Chriſt, the <hi>Sun of Righteouſnes;</hi> when they depart from the fountaine of light, life and living waters, they digge and drinke at the <hi>broken Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſternes</hi> of earth; they finde a little plaine, ſmooth, faire-promiſing plat of ground in the firſt <hi>Adam,</hi> and they dwell there; they take up their habitation in this Land of <hi>Shinar; Jeruſalem,</hi> the <hi>Viſion of peace,</hi> is built upon the High and Holy Hill of <hi>Sion,</hi> the Mountaine of the Lord; <hi>Babel,</hi> the confuſion of the creature is founded in the plaine of <hi>Shinar;</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Shinar,</hi> what it meaneth.</note> the low valley of the earthy Man. <hi>Shinar</hi> ſignifieth <hi>the watching of one aſleepe,</hi> or <hi>the changing of a City.</hi> The farther men goe from the Eaſt, the more they leave Chriſt (who awa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keneth the ſleepy, and giveth life to the dead) the more dull and drowſie they become, they watch
<pb facs="tcp:121297:5"/>and are awake no more then one that ſleepeth; they may have wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king dreames of <hi>Adams</hi> rich, full and plentifull ſtate, but when they ſhall awake in the ſpirit of Chriſt, it will be with them as with that hungry man, <hi>Eſ.</hi> 29.8. Or as with the Church of <hi>Laodicea.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rev.</hi> 3.</note> Thoſe that take ſanctuary, and ſeeke refuge in <hi>Adam</hi> and his perfection, do change a new and heavenly City for an old and earthy one.</p>
            <p>This City they build with brick made of the earth with hands, not of that linging ſtone cut out of the mountaine without hands: they lay the foundation of their Tower and City, upon <hi>Adams</hi> purity, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocency, righteouſneſſe, they pitch themſelves in <hi>Shinar, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This building upon the man, <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam,</hi> alwaies hath beene, ſtill is, and ever will be carried to a great height: ſome in every age of the world ſtrive to make it reach to a ſpirituall and divine nature, but the top thereof never yet touched Heaven: God blaſteth the building with confuſion, and calleth the
<pb facs="tcp:121297:6"/>worke <hi>Babel,</hi> before it can be finiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mar.</hi> 12.10 <hi>Luk.</hi> 17, 25</note> and al1 becauſe men will build with brick inſtead of ſtone; The Foundation and chiefe Corner ſtone is rejected of the builders: Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt in the ſpirit is ſleighted, as a meere <hi>Europia,</hi> a world in the Moone, a <hi>Chymaera,</hi> a Caſtle in the aire, having exiſtence onely in ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition, notion, and a deluded fancy. The language of men is confounded; one cals for Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tery, and a multiplyed Epiſcopacy is brought up; one cryes out, Here is Chriſt; another, Loe there he is; every man ſeeks to ſet up his form, and would have a ſhrine made for his owne <hi>Diana.</hi> Tis juſt with God to bring thoſe downe, and leave them below under fleſhly formes, and viſible, ſenſible appearances, who (like <hi>Peter</hi>) out of a drowſie and ſleepy temper, cannot be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tented with Chriſt alone in the ſpirit, and that righteouſneſſe of God in him, but muſt have a Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bernacle for <hi>Adam</hi> alſo when he apppeares (like <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Elias</hi>) in his glory.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:121297:6"/>
I foreſee the cavill and excepti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; ſome ſay and conclude, that I (and your Ladyſhip hath had your ſhare with me in the cenſure) deny all ſet order and eſtabliſhed forme of Church government. Theſe may goe to the plow-man for their an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer and ſatisfaction: He will tell them that by the continuall moti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of his Cart and Plow wheeles, he hath his buſineſſe done, whereas if they ſtood ſtill, he could have no ſeed ſowne, no crop reaped, nor a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny profit at all made of his land; yet in the revolution of the wheel, no ſpoke therein is alwayes fixed either upward or downward. In <hi>Ezekiels</hi> viſion you have a wheele in a wheele,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ez.</hi> 1.16.</note> an internall myſtery in an externall appearance, forme or diſpenſation; the ſpirit of life within keeps this wheele in moti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: God will have his people make a progreſſe; He will carry them from diſpenſation to diſpenſation; from ſtrength to ſtrength, and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver let them ſtand ſtill (in any forme) till they appeare in the perfection and beauty of the Spirit.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:121297:7"/>
Madam, I know you are remo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving from <hi>Shinar</hi> to <hi>Sion;</hi> from <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bylon</hi> the City of men, to <hi>Bethel</hi> the Houſe of God. Let it not trouble you to ſee the confuſions that are in the world, or in your owne heart, concerning the firſt <hi>Adam:</hi> there is good hope and great like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyhood that the building of the earthy ſtate will be at a ſtand. You are a gainer by changing rotten rags for rich, righteous and royall robes; there can be no loſſe of mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tality being ſwallowed up of life. I have heard one (and it hath been mine owne caſe) miſerably com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaining once of the confuſions, di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtractions and diviſion of heart; in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed the <hi>Babyloniſh</hi> yoke and cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tivity is a ſore bondage; fightings without, and feares within, trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles on every ſide, will give the fleſh no reſt; ſuch heavy and grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vous preſſures will make ſad and amaze a true <hi>Iſraelite,</hi> whoſe heart is upright before the Lord: Yet I told you (not long ſince) that <hi>John</hi> did grow and wax ſtrong in ſpirit in the Wilderneſſe,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>John</hi> ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifieth be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loved.</note>
               <hi>Luke</hi> 1.80. The
<pb facs="tcp:121297:7"/>ſeed of Gods love may lye under the rough, un-even, earthy clods and thoughts of mans heart; but will at laſt breake through, and grow up above them; this ſeed thrives in the night (of inſenſible<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and diſ-apprehenſion of the fleſh) as well as in the day (of ſight, ſenſe and feeling:) When man ſleepeth, as well as when he awaketh; in winter as well as in ſummer; the day and the night are the Lords; he made ſummer and winter; the ſharpe, cold and froſty winter nights of trouble and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſquiet are for the chaſtening of the weeds of fleſh, that the old and outward man may periſh, but that the inward and hidden man of the heart may be renewed day by day.<note place="margin">See 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.26, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </note> Divine favour is not of ſuch ſhal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low rooting as to dye and wither a way in the time of the creatures grudgings, murmurings and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſions.</p>
            <p>The Sun of Righteouſeſſe is not turned into darkneſſe, but gives light, and ſhineth in its ſtrength and glory to the coeleſtiall and ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall
<pb facs="tcp:121297:8"/>part and principle, when by reaſon of a cloudy skye of fleſhy frailties, it hath but a weak influ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence upon the terrene and ſenſible part of man. The way by which God will comfort his people throughly, is by conſuming their ſuppoſed comforts, and withering their carnall confidence. See <hi>Eſ.</hi> 40.1, &amp;c. to verſe 11. God would have his people comforted, and the Voice was to cry, <hi>All fleſh is graſſe, &amp;c.</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.7.</note>
               <hi>Adam</hi> was as the greene graſſe of the ground, and <hi>Eve</hi> was as the flower of the field, the glory of the earthy man: but neither the flow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, nor the graſſe, could endure the ſcorching heate of the Serpents temptation.<note place="margin">Ioh. 4.</note> The earthy and crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted excellency of the firſt <hi>Adam,</hi> is unto man as the Gourd was to <hi>Jo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nas:</hi> It may cover his head in the night, and give him the ſhadow of reſt and peace in his naturall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, and the time of his Igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance; but when the Sun ariſeth, when Jeſus Chriſt the greater light breaketh forth to diſcover the darkneſſe of that light, it withers
<pb facs="tcp:121297:8"/>away and ſhrinkes into nothing; this; like the <hi>Meteors</hi> and Glow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worme, hath its ſparke and ſplen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dor from the earthy glory; it ſhines onely, and is ſeene in the dark ſtate of the Creature: a worme at laſt, that deadly and never-dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing worme will ſmite the root of it: <hi>Adams</hi> righteouſneſſe will not, it cannot ſuccour the ſoule in the great and terrible day of the Lord.</p>
            <p>Two great rocks lye hid in the deep heart and ſea of mans nature, which make the voyage to heaven dangerous to the paſſengers; of which I would give your Ladyſhip warning before hand: earthy ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellency is one, the other is fleſhly Formes. The firſt derives its de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcent from <hi>Adam,</hi> and therfore will claime precedency and primogeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture; the ſecond, though they come into the world to wait upon the ſons and heires of God, during the time of their nonage and mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nority, yet would ſhare and divide the inheritance with the children, when they are of full age; the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant would abide in the houſe
<pb facs="tcp:121297:9"/>with the Sonne. The Church in her captivity complaines of two great evils, as the aggravation of her calamity,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Law.</hi> 5.2.8.</note>
               <hi>viz:</hi> Strangers poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing her Inheritance, and Servants ruling over her. Among all the vanities which <hi>Solomon</hi> ſaw under the Sun,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eccl.</hi> 10.7.</note> he took notice of Servants riding on horſe-backe, and Princes walking like Servants upon the earth.</p>
            <p>What a ſtage of Vanity is this world, where every Art and Sci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence is made up of madneſſe and folly? Would you not take it as an affront to your ſelfe, and a diſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragement to your friends, if a ſtranger, that lives upon the meere charitable benevolence of your Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, ſhould (by a baſe Paraſiticall inſinuation into your neare relati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons) bear more ſway in the family then your ſelfe? If a proud, ſaucy, malupert Intruder ſhould dip his hand in the diſh before you,<note place="margin">This you have ſeen, and had patience and borne it.</note> and moſt uncivilly ſnatch the meate from you? Sleight, ſcorne and jeer you to your face at Table? Would it not trouble you and undervalue
<pb facs="tcp:121297:9"/>your Fathers love, if you muſt make way to him by a baſe, beg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garly, upſtart fellow, who (like a Stage-player) hath but lately put off the rags of a ſlave, now appears in the habit of a Maſter? I came not <hi>(Madam)</hi> ſneaking under your Fathers roofe, to ſharke and ſlocke away your Treaſure and Jewels, but to warne your Ladyſhip of thoſe theeves and cheaters which lye in waite to ſteale and rob you of theſe heavenly treaſures, Joy, peace, comfort, and a quiet ſpirit. Created excellencyes and glory, the the faire ſhewes and ſpecious forms of the fleſh, are but ſtrangers and forraigners to the <hi>New Jeruſalem</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove, ſervants onely in <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> below; keepe your heart with all diligence, theſe elſe will ſlinke in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to it, flatter your fancy, deceive your underſtanding, delude your judgement, worke upon your will, cheate your affections, and keepe under the High-born Heire of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven Ieſus Chriſt, the King of Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe, and Prince of peace, ſhall be in low eſteenie, it once theſe get
<pb facs="tcp:121297:10"/>too much favour: This Prince muſt walke like a ſervant on earth; attend and waite upon the neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, wants, faults, frailties, and ſerve the ſinfull Righteouſneſſe of man ſo long,<note place="margin">Splendida peccata.</note> till he is wearied with his iniquities, Eſ. 43.24.</p>
            <p>I doe not proſtrate this ſmall Preſent to your Ladyſhip for Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tronage, but peruſe all; and though it come to your hands without former acquaintance, yet (I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve) not without a candid accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance. One part concernes you lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle, by the other you may get ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing. I muſt not live long with you, <hi>This</hi> may be a Teſtimony of my reſpects when I am gone from you. I came not to you to make my abode with you, but to put you in remembrance of your departing from your ſelfe. Your owne ſelfe is the laſt Cottage you live in here, and that but a poore, mean, earthy one neither: When this is diſſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, and, like a ſhepheards tent, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moved, your ſoule rakes poſſeſſion of an heavenly Manſion. When Selfe is conquered, the Soule is
<pb facs="tcp:121297:10"/>crownd: But this victory is not got not gained by might and power of fleſhly force, but by the ſpirit of the living God; all the auxiliary ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions and contributions of the firſt and naturall <hi>Adam,</hi> will not helpe ſo much as hinder in this combate and conflict; no leſſe then a coeleſtiall Army, a multitude of heavenly hoſts can doe this worke. Not he that boweth downe upon his knees, that kneeleth upon the ground, that worſhippeth in the earthy <hi>Adam,</hi> but he that keepeth on his legs, that ſtandeth on his feet, he that ſtandeth ſtedfaſt in the everlaſting Goſpell, Doctrine, Righteouſneſſe and faith of the Lord Ieſus the heavenly <hi>Adam<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> not he that lyeth downe and takes his reſt at the earthy ſprings and foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines of fleſhly, naturall, created perfection, excellency, joy, ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> but he that onely lap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peth and <hi>away</hi>): He hath that. <hi>Midia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſiſh</hi> man, that enemy Selfe, that carnall minde which is enmity a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt God: He it is, I ſay,<note place="margin">Canis ad Nilum.</note> that hath all enemies delivered in to his hands, and ſubdued under his feet. And
<pb facs="tcp:121297:11"/>yet how many forſake their feet, their wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king in Chriſt Jeſus the Lord, and the faith of the Goſpell; kneeling upon the ground of the earthy <hi>Adam,</hi> under pretence of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vorion and divine Worſhip to God. <hi>Gide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons</hi> ſouldiers were to be proved at the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>water, <hi>Iudg.</hi> 7.4, 5. And <hi>Iſrael</hi> provoked God at the waters, <hi>Pſal</hi> 106.32. Your tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all alſo is like to be at the waters of the firſt <hi>Adam,</hi> out of whom all humane glory and perfection (as ail things at the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning were brought out of thoſe waters, <hi>Gen.</hi> 1.2, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>) is produced, formed, and (as it were) created. Though Chriſt (like <hi>Gide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi>) bring you to the perfection (and further then that) of the natural and created ſtate, tis nor that you ſhould lye downe and live in it, but rather lap at it &amp; leave it. Cleanſe not your ſoul with water only, but bathe it in that open Fountain of water and bloud, <hi>Zech.</hi> 13.1. 1 <hi>Io.</hi> 5.6. This (like the river <hi>Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cos</hi>) will turn black into white,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eſ.</hi> 1.18.</note> ſcarlet and crimſon into the likenes of wool and ſnow: this is the <hi>Iordan</hi> in <hi>Iſrael,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Joh.</hi> 9.7.</note> where leproſyes are cleanſed, the pool of <hi>Siloam</hi> (or ſent, <hi>i.e,</hi> whither you are ſent) that reſtores to ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall ſight from naturall blindneſſe.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rev.</hi> 3.18.</note>
            </p>
            <p>The gold I preſent your Ladyſhip with may happily be ſoyld a little on the outſide, by the earthen veſſell it is brought in; an expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rimentall conſtruction &amp; a ſpirituall inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pretation will make it bright &amp; gliſtering. I know no other treaſure that will enrich your heart, nor is there any thing elſe worth your acceptance, fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the hand of him whoſe heart doth, &amp; ever will exceedingly rejoice in the proſperity and ſtability of your foul.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:121297:11"/>
            <head>What was ſaid to the Generall at <hi>Windſor,</hi> as it was written in a Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſhortly after it was ſpoken.</head>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>Brother,</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N my laſt by <hi>H. W.</hi> the Carrier, I intimated ſomewhat to you, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning my preſent condition; which if you ſhould heare of by o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, might happily be miſ-reported unto you, and raiſe ſome jealouſy and trouble of ſpirit in you, and the reſt of my friends.</p>
                  <p>Therefore that you may know the cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainty of my ſtate, I doe, with mine owne hand write unto yon, and ſhall truly inform you of things; more particularly of ſuch as reſpect my relation to rhe Army.</p>
                  <p>When I lay at <hi>Autrie,</hi> in <hi>Devonſhire,</hi> the Lord began to confound my thoughts con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the preſent Warre; my ſpirit was much taken off from following that courſe
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:121297:12"/>any longer, as a way that God ſeemed to have left, and therefore ſhould wither and dye; but he would ſet up his Kingdome, and bring forth his own glory, and his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples ſafety, another way. Strong reaſonings there were <hi>Pro</hi> and <hi>Con,</hi> and many diſputes in my heart, whether to leave the Army then, or no: during which conflict in my ſelfe, my Colonell, Mr <hi>John Pickering,</hi> fell ſicke and died. By his death the Lord ſeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to ſatisfie me, and to put an end to all my enquiries; I thought that it was his mind and will that I ſhould abide no long<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er in that way: With this I ſate down well contented for a time.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Decemb.</hi> 16. I buried my Col: at <hi>Lyme,</hi> without any cuſtomary ceremony at all, and the next day departed, with a reſolution not to returne againe to exerciſe, or to be conſidered in the notion of a Chaplaine to the Regiment any more: Of which reſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion I privately acquainted one or two of my friends, but did not publickly take my leave of the Regiment, for my heart was not quite taken off from thoſe worldly advanta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges which came in that way. Then I came through the coaſts to viſit my friends, among whom I was ſilent, though I had great di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſputes ſtill in my ſelfe, and was at much un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certainty in my ſpirit, whether to fir ſtill or no. I durſt not diſcover my minde unto you, and the reſt of my friends, for feare that either I ſhould grieve you, or that you would perſwade mee contrary to my owne will. So I came to <hi>London,</hi> where I acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted ſome friends with my thoughts and
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:121297:12"/>workings of heart, and deſired them to find out ſome way of employment for me; for I was not weary of the Army onely, but (ſuch as it was) of my Miniſtry too. They told mee I was under a temptation , and wiſhed me not to give place to the Devill. With much love and good intention, they perſwaded me to proceed, not conſidering that the Lord is blaſting and breaking downe this <hi>Antichriſtian</hi> and <hi>Babyloniſh</hi> forme of Miniſtry now ſo much magnified in <hi>England,</hi> and that he will put a more pure, faithfull andeffectuall miniſtry into the hands of his Saints. Many worldly and carnall arguments they urged to me, ſuch as my owne covetous and deceitſull heart had laid hold on before, but now ſtucke more cloſely unto, being preſt againe by friends: So I tooke up new reſolutions, and did re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne againe to the Army, to that which I had lately vomited up, my dogged nature barking at the approach and appearing of God.</p>
                  <p>But God, who is juſt and holy in all his wayes, purſued me with a ſtrong winde, his ſpirit wrought trouble and diſquiet in me, and rai ſed a continuall tempeſt in, and round about me all the while I lay, and remained in this broken barke and ſplitted ſhip, unto which I had committed my ſelfe for ſecurity, eaſe and perfect honour; for ſuch like were the motives of my returne and entrance againe into the Army: onely for a little ſeaſon I had ſome calme in my ſpirit, when the Army was marching to <hi>London,</hi> with engaged reſolutions to follow
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:121297:13"/>truth and righteouſneſſe, and to oppoſe op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion, cruelty, violence, corruption and injuſtice among men in the earth, though of place, power, and abuſed authority: here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in I was carried with all freedome, peace, clearneſſe and cheerfuleſſe of ſpirit. But when men began to neglect their under ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kings, to falſifie their vowes, to turne aſide and corrupt their wayes before the Lord, I was at a ſtand. But my dull and dark heart could not ſee the end of the Lord, till hee ſent a voice into the Wilderneſſe, and after that a Viſion into his Temple; then I di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcerned the way of the Almighty. While I walked in my confuſions and diſtractions, as in a wilderneſſe, the Voice cryed by Mr <hi>Sedgwick</hi> and Mr <hi>Saltmarſh,</hi> Forſake, For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake, and come out of theſe crooked and carnall wayes and pathes, and come into more ſtrict and ſpirituall courſes and enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments: I heard the ſound of words, as. of a mighty ruſhing winde, but could not tell whence it came; I did not clearly under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand that it was of the Lord, but thought it had been the ſtrong workings of their own melancholly and private fancyes: nor could I tell whether it would goe; I did not know that the Lord would breath into my heart the ſame or the like evidences which were given to them, nor did he as yet. But after this winde came an Earthquake, which ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked my earthly, carnall and worldly frame; the oppoſitions, diſputes and reaſonings of my earthly heart began to be moved; obje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions came in amaine, and my diſtractions encreaſed: Sometimes the fleſh (and Satan
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:121297:13"/>together) would put me forward with mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives of pride, vain-glory, ſingularity, po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pular applauſe, getting a name, becom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing famous, eminent and be taken no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice of, as Mr. <hi>Sedgwick,</hi> Mr. <hi>Saltmarſh</hi> were: and why ſbould not I ſay ſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing as well as they? By and by I was diſcouraged upon the ſame grounds; and thus the temptation wrought; Why ſhould I ſo play the hypocrite and ſeek the the prayſe of men? And thus I was tortu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red between two, and lay in a trembling condition: the two ſeeds, the two Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, Fleſh and Spirit ſtrove in the wombe of my heart together: fleſhly fear and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcouragements, fleſhly pride and boldneſſe ſtriving which ſhould come forth firſt.<note place="margin">Fleſhly fear, diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couragements, pride and boldneſſe one Seed, the ſpirit, the other Seed.</note> But before either could come to the birth the the Spirit caught it by the heel, and made it halt that it could not riſe to its height, nor run to its end.</p>
                  <p>This earthquake within me removed me from <hi>London, Decemb.</hi> 11. 1647. I could not reſt till I went to <hi>Windſor</hi> to eaſe my thoughts before the General and ſome o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers. <hi>Decemb.</hi> 13. I came thither: my ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jections and confuſions followed me, and lay ſore upon me. The next day I preſt into the Generall Counſell of War, where I was tormented between fear and bold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe. My time was then; fain I would have ſpoken , and was almoſt angry with God, becauſe he would nor ſuffer me: but the Lords time was not yet; and an anſwer was given into me that (the Commiſſioners o Parliament being there, to whom I haf
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:121297:14"/>no word from the Lord) it was not ſeaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable.</p>
                  <p>When I was thus ſilenced, a fire follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the earthquake, and entred into my bones and bowels, for that (an occaſion being offered by L. G. <hi>Cromwell</hi> ſeeing me there, and coming to me with much cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſie and reſpect) I ſpake a few words un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him, but not to his ſatisfaction nor mine becauſe of the preſent buſineſſe of the Councell interrupting. This fire or new wine of the Lord wrought in my body be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond the uſuall and accuſtomed manner and meaſure after my travell and change of ayre. Still I endeavoured to disbur then my thoughts to the Generall or ſome others of the Army, but I found no convenient op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity for that end, for the Lord was not in the winde, earthquake, or fire, ſo as to bring forth what he had formed in me; I thought that was not the time, nor place, nor way, wherein God would ſpeak by me, and therefore reſolved to return to London and ſend my minde in writing to the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my. As I was reſolving thus to do, a ſmall ſtill voyce (and but ſmall and very ſtill) Came unto me, ſet me upon my legs, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed my ſpirit, ſilenced all my carnall rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonings and diſputes, made me ſir down in quiet aſſurance and confident expectation from the Lord, bid me go yet again to the Generall, and told me,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Dec.</hi> 18.</note> He would be with me. So I went in a dark miſty morning, and as Iwas going, it was ſaid unto me, that I ſhould ſpeak unto them in a day like their condition, full of clouds and darkneſſe.
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:121297:14"/>When I came to the Generals Quarters, I found him in the orchard alone; with all reverence and reſpect I addreſſed my ſelfe unto him, though it is reported that I ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver put off my hat, nor gave him any ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour at all: I told him that I had a meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage to him, and muſt intreat his patience to hear it. Hedeſired me to walk into the houſe, and ſaid, he would come preſently, and nothing ſbould interrupt his hearing of what I had to ſay. When he came in, I applyed my ſelf to his Excellency, and (af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſome digreſſion cauſed by the Scout<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maſter) I ſpake more particularly to this effect unto him.</p>
                  <p>Sir, you are (like <hi>Ephraim</hi>) oppreſſed and broken in judgement, you know not what to do, nor which way to turn; your underſtanding is loſt, your counſell and wiſdome blaſted; you know not how to manage or diſpoſe your Army as formerly you have don; all which the General confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed. Thus (ſaid I) you are at a loffe eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry way; and all becauſe like <hi>Ephraim,</hi> you have willinglyfollowed after the commands of men, and not of God Then he was pleaſed to give me a particular account of his Principles and Actions, in reference to the war, from his firſt taking up of Armes unto that day. The Parliament, he ſaid, was his Mother, and put the ſword into his hand; which he never took up to pul down authority, but to relieve the oppreſſed. I replyed, true, Sir, the Parliament was your mother that brought you forth, and gave you life and power to act in the way yon
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:121297:15"/>have don; it put the ſword into your hand to ſuppreſſe the violence of the oppreſſour; yea, the Lord of hoſts was with you as a mighty man of war; he guided your conn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rell and ſtrengthned your hand; he cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red your head, and kept you in the day of battell went before you, and chaſed your enemy; he gave you ſucceſſe and vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctory; proſpered your deſignes; and did great and wouderfull things by you. But your mother the Parliament, became un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſt, corrupt, and oppreſſing; the Lord bid you <hi>plead with this your mother, as an harlot, and a wife of whordome.</hi> You did ſo, and did well in ſo doing: you refuſed to diſband, you engaged with the Army ro do juſtice, to relieve the oppreſſed,<note place="margin">Hoſ. 2.2.</note> to purge the Houſes, &amp;c. you came to <hi>London</hi> with that reſolution, but have neglected to do what you promiſed, and now the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome cryes and groans under your neglect as much as under the former oppreſſions. God hath perſwaded me that you will bear with me, and therefore I ſhall with all free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome and plainneſſe ſpeak unto your Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellency what is in my heart.</p>
                  <p>Sir, You have committed great adultery and defiled your ſelf with much uncleannes; you clime up into the bed of a ſtrumpet, a whore and an aduſterous woman: for now the Commiſſioners of Parliament are here, you joyn and mix your counſels with them, and will do nothing without them, though they remain in the ſtate they were, when you firſt pleaded againſt them; only the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leven Members are withdrawn; and yet you
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:121297:15"/>think to ſettle this Nation in peace and qiuetneſſe. But what peace ſo long as the witchcrafts and whordoms are ſo many? No, God will weaken your hands, and wither your hopes; yon ſhall not proſper as you have done, becauſe you have forſaken the Rock of Iſrael. The neglect of their un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertakings: the Generall did (for the moſt part) confeſſe, but ſomethings he excuſed. Moreover concerning the Army, I ſayd:</p>
                  <p>The whole Army is like unto an Iſland of Willowes, confuſion and diſtraction compaſſeth it about like waters; they nor you have not any bridge or boat to get out; you know not vvhich vvay to turn or go for ſafety; your own counſels and po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licies, your carnall reaſon and Wiſdome in vvhich you now act ſo much; ſome ſudden flaſhes of Repentance and Reformation all theſe and the like give you up and bind you till the enemy hath put out vour eyes, brought you to his mill and made ſport with yee. Other things fell in to diſcourſe, as touching Mr. <hi>Sedgwick,</hi> Mr. <hi>Saltmarſh,</hi> and the Agitators, which I ſhall omit; theſe things were ſo faſtned and lay ſo ſore on my ſpirit two or three dayes before I ſpake to the Generall, that I could by no means ſhake them off, till I had caſt them at his ſeet. No ſooner had I delivered my meſſage, but my bowels were ſetled, and the vvhole frame of my body reduced to a good temper again. The Generall gave eare to all that I ſaid with much candour and clemency, took all in good part and (as aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards alſo by Mr. <hi>Peters</hi> gave me thanks
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:121297:16"/>for my plain dealing, as he cal'd it; ſo I bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wed before him and took my leave.</p>
                  <p>The next day Mr <hi>Peters</hi> vvas to preach in the morning, and I in the afternoone; hard cenſures and concluſions were put up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on my ſermon, by ſome from vvhom (a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle before) J had received thanks for it: but the Lord ſhewed me ſo plainly from vvhat ſpirit it proceeded in them, that I had no cauſe at all of Repentance for any thing I had ſaid; and if there had been a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny that had taken my ſermon of vvhom I might have had the notes, I vvould have publiſhed it vvith this Relation for all to judge.</p>
                  <p>My buſineſſe being now ended I vvas ſnatched from thence with a ſtrong hand (<hi>Decemb.</hi> 21.) and carried on my vvay re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joycing: that night I came to Sir <hi>Thomas Evelings</hi> in <hi>Surrey;</hi> early in the morning before day (<hi>Decemb.</hi> 23.) as I vvas lying in my bed (Major <hi>Axel</hi> lying a ſleepe by me) my ſleep brake from me, and the Lord ſuffered Satan to tempt me; J vvas fearfull at firſt to open my eyes, leſt J ſhould ſee ſome ghaſtly and ugly ſight to amaze me; but it vvas told me that J ſhould ſee no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to affright; ſo vvas the Lord graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly pleaſed to indulge my vveakneſſe. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſtrengthned and incouraged thus from on high, I opened my eyes, but ſaw no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing as yet to aſtoniſh me. The Tempter came upon me vvith much eagerneſſe and violence, tooke hold of both mine armes, ſpread them abroad, held me dovvn and ſtrove earneſtly to get into me, but could
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:121297:16"/>not. My fleſh at firſt was ſomewhat a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frayd, but no ſooner did fear ariſe, but in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantly the Lord appeared in me, in the midſt of my body, ten thouſand times brighter then the Sun, and ſpake in me ſo plainly, that 100000 witneſſes cannot make it ſo ſure unto me; that it was Hee that ſpake unto me, as his own voice did, vvhich ſaid? Stronger am I vvithin then hee that is vvithout thee, and withall threw off the Tempter as a very vveak thing, as little &amp; as light as a feather. Preſently after he came and appeared before me, but ſtood at a di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance and durſt not come neer me, for the Lord yet ſtayd with me and in me, and J plainly perceived that he vvas afrayd of the glorious power and Majeſty, vvhich was my breaſt-plate and bulwarke; yet he ſtood vaunting &amp; vaporing &amp; breathing out high threatnings againſt me. He upbraided me with ſingularity and vain glory, and charged me that what I had done at the Head-quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters I had done altogether in hypocriſie. Upon the accuſation my fleſh contracted ſome guilt; for (as I told you) the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceitfulneſſe of my heart did much to put me on, and pull me back before I went; and yet I can truly ſay, that with integrity and ſingleneſſe of heart, and in faithfulneſſe to God J diſcharged my ſelf in this matter: how this ſhould be, you will eaſily diſcern, if you know what the two Natures, the two Men are; what the two Nations, Seedes, principles, with their different inclinations, motions, actions in Man are. But to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed: No ſooner did guilt begin to faſten
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:121297:17"/>but immediately the Lord ſet himſelfe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Satan, and ſaid; Take away the fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy garments from him; he ſpake further with invincible evidence, and ſaid, Iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty is not there; ſinne is at an end; the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked one cometh and findeth nothing: Now is the Accuſer of the Brethren caſt out. Theſe words though J heard them not with the ear of Senſe, were ſpoken with ſuch a mighty, powerfull, and effectuall demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration of truth, life and glory, that in the ſtrength of them J can ſtand againſt the contradictions of the whole World; and ſuch indeed was their efficacy, that the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill inſtantly did fly and ſhrinke away with ſuch ſhame and ſilence as you cannot ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine. Now (and never till now) did I know what juſtification is, and what it is to have God ſo nigh as to juſtify: J underſtood the Notion of it long ſince, J mean Notional<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly; and was ſo far acquainted with it, as to have much peace and comfortable ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectation from it, but infinitely ſhort of this; for this was ſo glorious, excellent, and tranſcendent that it is impoſſible for me to expreſſe it.</p>
                  <p>All ſtormes were blown over, and my ſoul being ſweetly received into the viſion of Peace, that City where it would be; not long after J ſell into a ſlumbering ſleep, and in a dream, me thought J heard my Dear friend Mr. <hi>Bacon,</hi> preaching in one of the publike places, with much plainneſſe and weakneſſe of ſpeech, but with great power and demonſtration of the Spirit; his do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine was malicionſly oppoſed by an elo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:121297:17"/>young man with great Wiſdome and excellency of fleſh and humane accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſhments, whoſe mouth was ſoon ſtopt by Col. <hi>Har.</hi> Many of rude behaviour come forth curſing and banning at his doctrine, and exclaiming on him for an heretick, ſciſmatique, &amp;c. This alſo was given into as the interpretation of it, viz. that the appearances of God in a higher and more ſpirituall way then formerly ſhall be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradicted and blaſphemed, by Jew rather then by Gentile, by profeſſors more then by profane, by proteſtant more then by pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſt, by thoſe that keep their Church (as they ſay) rather then by thoſe that know no Church at all. If every dayes experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence doth not bring in too full a teſtimony hereunto, J ſhall be contended to be ſo ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted of as <hi>Joſeph</hi> was by his brethren. <hi>Gen.</hi> 37.19.</p>
                  <p>Yeſterday in the morning (<hi>Decem.</hi> 27) as J was lying in my bed at Mr. <hi>Smiths</hi> in <hi>Cheapſide,</hi> the Devill came again and got under my left ſhoulder, moved a little, and left me: J know he ſhall never ſet upon my Right arm, my ſtrength, and power, which is of, and in the Lord: he may come on my left ſide and ſtir a little in the infir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities and weakneſſes of the fleſh, but the Spirit luſteth againſt him ſo, that he cannot do the evill that he would: the Lord is ſo rebuking him that J begin to lay my hand on the Dragons den, and the neſt of the Adder, to come neer the hole of the Aſp, to play with the Serpent and Cockatrice without hurt or fear: J could ſhew you the
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:121297:18"/>meaning of this more plainly, and tell you of my further priviledges, but J forbear be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe J know what the World will ſay.</p>
                  <p>Theſe things J have written to you that you may not be troubled at any; rumor whatſoever which ſhall ariſe concerning me; but know that the Lord is with me, and hath given me to rejoyce in reproach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es and evill ſpeeches, as well as in the praiſe of men.<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Ro</hi> 10.6, 7, 8.</note> The ſame Lord is nigh unto every one that waiteth for him; yea, he is over all, and in all, that you ſhall not need to goe hither and thither to ſeek him, but rather look for him within you, and wait for his riſing out of his ſepulchre of the fleſh, even the fleſh, who at his appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring will bring life and immortality, to light. Fare you well.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Your loving brother, <hi>Henry Pinnell.</hi>
                     </signed> 
                     <dateline>
                        <hi>London,</hi> 
                        <date>
                           <hi>Decem.</hi> 28. 2647.</date>
                     </dateline>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>I know I ſhall ſeem as a Dreamer and a Deceiver to many; as an inſolent &amp; proud
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:121297:18"/>man for what J have ſaid of the Parliament and Army; but my anſwer to all that cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure me, is:</p>
            <p>Firſt, It is a very ſmall thing with me to be judged of man, or to ſtand in mans judgement day; and therefore no ſuch thing moveth me at all.</p>
            <p>Secondly, J bleſſe God who overcame my fears and fraylties, and made me faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full and bold to diſcharge the duty which then he layd upon me, and required of me; his ſpirit moved me to ſpeak, and hath (to this very day) ſealed and ſetled upon me an abundant great reward of much more peace and joy then J ſhould have had for my ſilence; though J ſeem as a deceiver to men, yet was J true to him that truſted me.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, Thoſe that judge me, let them tell me, Why God did not give up Jſrael into the hand of their enemies after he had threatned to deliver them no more, (<hi>Judg.</hi> 10.13.) without any reſtriction or limita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of their amendment or returning to him: or why he did not deſtroy <hi>Nineveh</hi> when he had ſent <hi>Jonas</hi> peremptorily to denounce ruine againſt that City without exception of repentance or reformation, <hi>Jon.</hi> 1.2. &amp; 3.4. Jf it be ſaid that God ſecretly reſerved in himſelfe the condition of their humiliation, and ſo would not overthrow them, as he had threatned; but reſpite, ſuſpend; yea, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together divert and withhold his judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment from them, in caſe they did repent; though there be no ſuch thing expreſſed:
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:121297:19"/>I demand then, whether or noe God doth not ſtill retaine the ſame preroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive and liberty in himſelfe now, as he did then? And therefore whether men now commanded to declare the meſſage of God to any people or perſons, are to bee cenſured of, being led by a ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſpirit, though the thing ſpoken by them doe not come to paſſe any more, then that which <hi>Jonah</hi> ſaid of <hi>Nine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veh?</hi> And though God may ſuffer an evill and hurtfull Angell (during the time of Antichriſts Reigne) to with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold the foure windes from blowing on the Sea or Land, yet where hath hee bound himſelfe from looſing thoſe windes againe, and powring out the ſpirit of propheſy upon his people?</p>
            <p n="4">4. If ſome may take liberty to revile and reproach the Authority of Parliament, and that in the hearing of ſome of their mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers, without any controule or checke: If ſome (and they of the more ſtrict and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe ſort of Presbyterian Preachers too) may have the freedome to ſcandalize and aſperſe the moſt faithfull men of the Army, accuſing them of errours, ſchiſmes, hereſies, &amp;c. as I have heard ſome of them doe, though they confeſſe they never ſpake with thoſe men they thus charge: why then may not others take the boldneſſe (from better grounds, and in a more honeſt way) to ſpeake as freely to the faces either of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament men, or Officers, or Commanders of the Army, and reprove them for ſuch miſcarriages, which they will not deny
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:121297:19"/>themſelves to be guilty of? For my owne part, I have not ſpoken ſo much behind the backe of any of them, as I have, or would doe to their faces, eſteeming it a baſe and diſhoneſt thing to doe other wiſe.</p>
            <p n="5">5. Neither am I any whit diſpleaſed (as he was, <hi>Jon:</hi> 4.1.) at the proſperity, good ſucceſſe, and ſtrange victories, which God, in much mercy to this Kingdom, hath won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfully crowned the Army with ſince I left it; I have the teſtimony of a good conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to rejoyce in: If I was deceived, I can boldly ſay, the Lord did deceive me; and, if he will have it ſo, it is better for me (who am but one) to dye in the repute and cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit of all men, and be counted a lyar, rather then the whole Nation (or ſo many godly in it) ſhould periſh. But</p>
            <p n="6">6. The thing is ſulfilled already to mee; for the Army, which once was ſo beautifull &amp; lovely in mine eye, is now become moſt blacke and ugly, God having made me aſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med of fleſhly confidence therein.</p>
            <p>I am yet confident of what I ſaid to ſome at <hi>Windſor,</hi> who asked me about the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>banding of the Army, <hi>i. e.</hi> That it ſhall lye as one mountaine in the ſcale againſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother; as one hill in the ballance againſt, another; as one potſheard to daſh againſt another; It is a veſſell wherein is no plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, fitted onely to breake and to be bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken.</p>
            <p>And though I know there are many pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious Saints of ſeverall diſpenſations in it, yet ſhall they more and more relinquiſh
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:121297:20"/>that way, as they grow up to more immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate and more ſpirituall enjoyments. As God guideth and goeth before every man, ſo let him walke, and let his name be prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb n="19" facs="tcp:121297:20"/>
            <head>A little of the firſt <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam,</hi> and how occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſioned.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Mr Baker,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hen I was at <hi>Dale</hi> (<hi>June</hi> 25.) you know my diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe in publique was upon <hi>Jo.</hi> 9. At which diſcourſe you tooke great offence, as ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peares both by your carriage towards me, and your charge a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt me; which two things I ſhall (as I told you) bring to publique examination, that they may have an open tryall, and have verdict paſſe upon them accordingly.</p>
            <p n="1">
               <note place="margin">Your car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage.</note> 1. Your carriage, as I told you, when I had endeavoured and obtained a confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence with you; I thought was very unci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill, unjuſt, and altogether unbeſeeming a profeſſing Chriſtian , much more a reall Saint, contrary to the rules of right Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, and the Royall law of Love. For after I had ended my diſcourſe, you neither pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded any thing preſently, wherein you were unſatisfied, in a faire, friendly and
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:121297:21"/>brotherly way; nor did you come or ſend to me to receive ſatisfaction concerning my opinion or doctrine, which might happily be miſ-underſtood, either by your hearing or my ſpeaking; which it you had don, I ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe would have beene the moſt probable way to preſerve unity and peace; and I ſhould very gladly have embraced any ſuch overture from yor, but (contrary to the principles of true Chriſtianity) you did ſlan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derouſly report of me behind my back, bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly inveighing againſt my doctrine, going from one to another, and diſſwading them from hearing mo, as being a moſt dangerous and erroneous way, every way labouring to vilify and make me odious, that my per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon and preaching might be brought into contempt and ſcorne. When I met you at <hi>Hophill,</hi> you did peremptorily juſtifie and maintaine all that you had ſaid and done, as honeſt and lawfull. This was your behavi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our; now whether it be ſutable to the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpell or no; let all men judge, nay judge your ſelfe.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Whether it be ſutable ſo much as to the Law? I know you contend much for the Law to be your rule of life. Doth the Law teach you to order your converſation thus? Doth the Law alow you to murther your neighbours name, to robbe and ſteale from him his credit and reputation among men? Doe you (like thoſe Jewes, <hi>Jer.</hi> 7.4.9.) cry the Law of the Lord, the Law of the Lord is our rule, and yet backbite, ſtander, and maliciouſly detract contrary to the Law? You that make your boaſt of the Law,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:121297:21"/>through breaking the Law diſhonour you God? Surely the Uncircumciſion that keep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth and fulfilleth the righteouſneſſe of the Law,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ro.</hi> 2.23. <hi>V.</hi> 26, 27.</note> ſhall judge and condemn the Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſion, which by the letter tranſgreſſeth the Law: there be ſome that are led by the Law of the ſpirit of life in Chriſt Jeſus: who (though they are accounted carnall, looſe and licentious, yet) live more holily then thoſe that are <hi>Moſes</hi> Diſciples, and pretend ſo much unto the letter: though they be as without a Law, yet are they not ſo to Chriſt and God. Whileſt you juſtifie your errone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and irregular actions, you prove your ſelfe a downright <hi>Antinomian,</hi> one that in words pleadeth for the Law, but walks di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectly contrary to it in practiſe.</p>
            <p n="2">2 In dealing thus with me have you ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved the law of equity or morall honeſty, doing as you would be done by? Or is your name and credit ſo little worth, that you care not how it be traduced?</p>
            <p n="3">3. Doth not the Scripture ſay, that a man is not to be rejected as a Heretike, till after the firſt and ſecond admonition?<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Tit.</hi> 3.10: <hi>Mat.</hi> 18.</note> And that a brother is to be dealt with as a bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, before he be caſt off? Wherein have you walked thus towards me? In reviling me and my doctrine behind my backe, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore you ever admoniſhed me to my face? Is the Scripture your rule? Is this your walk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing up to it? Or would you be counted an <hi>Anti-Scripturiſt?</hi> Who is now the erroneous man, Mr <hi>Baker?</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. When men ſhall ſee and hear of your practiſe to be ſo contrary to the peace, pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:121297:22"/>and profeſſion of the Goſpell, how can you eſcape the cenſure of a ſeditious per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, a railer, a backbiter, a factious Schiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matick, cauſing diviſion, ſtrife and conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, not endeavouring to keepe the unity of the ſpirit in the bond of peace, as you ought to doe?</p>
            <p>Neither hath the rancour and venome of your tongue kept within the bounds of <hi>Derbyſhire,</hi> but the poiſon thereof is ſpread as farre as <hi>Nottingham</hi> already; for I heare that your Brother the Schoolmaſter in that place hath (as diſhoneſtly as your ſelfe) de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>famed me there alſo. If what he hath ſaid be by your inſtigation, you muſt be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tented to bear the greateſt ſhare of his miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carriage; if not, he hath brought his owne good behaviour into queſtion, and muſt beare all the burden himſelfe. It is reported by him that I deny the two Sacraments (ſo called) the Supper, and Baptiſme: Upon what grounds I know nor, for I never had any diſcourſe with him; I doe not know your Brother, nor doth he (I ſuppoſe) know me: I believe yee are brethren, your car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage is ſo much alike.</p>
            <p>But becauſe he hath interpoſed between us with his new raiſed rumour,<note place="margin">Digreſſion.</note> I ſhall ſtep aſide to ſpeake a word to thar, and then re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>returne to the examination of your charge,</p>
            <p n="1">1. For the Supper.</p>
            <p>Firſt, I never forbad the uſe thereof to any untill the coming of Chriſt.</p>
            <p>Secondly, If by the coming of Chriſt you underſtand it according to the vulgar ſenſe;
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:121297:22"/>for his laſt coming at the end of the world: I leave you and every man to your faith therein. But</p>
            <p>Thirdly, Why may not the coming of Chriſt, and that <hi>(untill be come)</hi> be under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood of that coming of Chriſt in the ſpirit, which he foretold before his departing out of the body.</p>
            <p n="2">2. As for Baptiſme, I leave you and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers alſo to the freedome of your faith therein. But if you will impoſe the obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation therof, and the obedience thereunto upon me as to an Ordinance, I muſt firſt be ſatisfied.</p>
            <p>Firſt, Whether <hi>(by Baptiſme)</hi> you un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand Poedo-baptiſm, Childiſh-baptiſm, or the Baptiſme of Children? If ſo, then where is either your precept or pattern for ſo doing? Or</p>
            <p>Secondly, If you will have Baptiſme of water to be reſtrained, and to belong only to thoſe that are adult and of ripe yeares; yet then, where is your authority from any inſtitution of Chriſt after his reſurrection, who had before by his death put an end to foregoing Types and Figures of himſelfe? Therefore,</p>
            <p n="1">1. That place (<hi>Mat.</hi> 18.19.) will not hold <hi>Water,</hi> nor ſerve your turne at all in the ſenſe you urge it, and would have it brought unto; for thoſe words <hi>(into the Name)</hi> doe rather exclude then imply, in, into, or with water.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Nor is it enough that you tell mee of the Apoſtles practiſe, that they did baptize <hi>(with water)</hi> and that after the reſurrecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:121297:23"/>and aſcenſion of Chriſt, unleſſe you pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce a warrant from Chriſt, authorizing them ſo to doe, and commanding them and us, by way of injunction, to ſubmit unto it, as a neceſſary and binding duty. But I ſay,</p>
            <p>Firſt, If you will make the practiſe of the Apoſtles your rule in one thing, why not in another, the ground and authority being equall for both, and therefore both alike binding? And then, why doe you not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noint your ſicke with oyle, as the Apoſtles did,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ja.</hi> 5.14.</note> and as <hi>Iames</hi> commandeth you? Is the uſe and virtue of anointing loſt, and doth the efficacy of Baptiſme laſt? Will water keepe longer then oyle? Againe; why doe you not circumciſe, as <hi>Paul</hi> did? You will ſay, Circumciſion is aboliſhed, but Baptiſme is not: Was <hi>Iohn</hi> any more then a ſervant, as <hi>Moſes</hi> was? vvhy then muſt he abide in the Houſe of God, when the Son himſelf is come? I doe not find that <hi>Paul</hi> did repent for ſhaking hands with <hi>Moſes</hi> in circumci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing <hi>Timothy,</hi> more then he did for ſaluting <hi>Iohn,</hi> in baptizing ſome of the <hi>Corinthians.</hi> Yet,</p>
            <p>Secondly, I deny not, but that the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles might have an indulgent diſpenſation given unto them, ſutable to the infancy of the Church then, as others may have now anſwerable to the lowneſſe and weakneſſe of the faith of ſome in theſe daies, whom I leave to ſtand or fall to their owne Maſter. But if Baptiſm be enforced as a Law, I ſhall queſtion two things, and very much ſcru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple.</p>
            <p n="1">
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:121297:23"/>
1. VVhether it be not an <hi>adding</hi> to the Booke of God to interline and inſert the Baptiſm of Children into the Bible, when there is no ſuch thing mentioned by Chriſt or his Apoſtles in all the New Teſtament, either by way of Command or Cuſtome?</p>
            <p n="2">2. VVhether to conclude Baptiſm of water, &amp; ſo conſequently to impoſe it on any, from that in <hi>Mat.</hi> 28.19 be not a part of will wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip; a making void the command of Chriſt by mens <hi>traditions;</hi> and a <hi>taking away from the Booke of God?</hi> For whereas Chriſt there brings up Baptiſme to its height, fulneſſe, glory, purity and perfection; ſome goe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout to empty, weaken and make void the ſenſe and ſcope of that Scripture, by apply<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>that</hi> to water, which Chriſt <hi>expreſly</hi> at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tributeth and appropriateth to the Father, Himſelfe and the Spirit.</p>
            <p>I have not the faith to believe, that the Ratiocinations and arguments of men, the concluſions, inferences and inductions of Reaſon are ſufficient to make any Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance in the Church of Chriſt, without an immediate, plaine, direct,<note place="margin">M. Denne, M. Tomes, &amp;c.</note> punctuall and divine inſtitution from Chriſt. But enough hath beene ſaid of this by others already: Therefore, Mr <hi>Baker,</hi> I ſhall paſſe from the manner of your carriage, and come to exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine the matter of your charge.</p>
            <p n="1">
               <note place="margin">You charge</note>1. <hi>You charge me that I ſhould ſay the firſt</hi> Adam <hi>was borne (or created) blind; and this, you ſay, is errour, hereſy and falſe doctrine.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, I did ſay that every man, by nature,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:121297:24"/>is borne blind, in reſpect of diſcerning the things of God, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.14.</p>
            <p>Secondly, I ſaid alſo, That the <hi>firſt Adam</hi> in his created ſtate was blind, as to the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding of the <hi>Myſtery</hi> of God in Chriſt to be revealed unto him, or as to the true knowledge of himſelfe and the condition he was then in. He had the ſight of ſenſe, he ſaw his wife, the tree and the apple that he did eate; but he had not a ſight of the imperfection and ſhortneſſe of the preſent ſtate he was then in, to that which he was afterwards to be raiſed up unto, in Chriſt. For,</p>
            <p n="1">1. If he had <hi>knowne</hi> the property of the Tree of life, (which repreſented Chriſt) he would not have forſaken and rejected it, but rather how eaten of the fruit thereof, that he might have lived; as the Apoſtle ſpeakes, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.8. If the Princes of this world had <hi>known</hi> the <hi>Wiſedome</hi> of God, they would not have crucified the Lord Jeſus: If <hi>Adam</hi> that was the chiefeſt and moſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent in knowledge above all other crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures in the world; if he had knowne the myſtery of Chriſt in the Tree of life, hee would not have beene ſeduced by the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent to ſeeke his perfection in the forbid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den fruit. Man that is ignorant of Gods Righteouſneſſe, goeth about to eſtabliſh his owne, <hi>Rom.</hi> 10.3.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Why elſe is not the opening of their eyes affirmed of <hi>Adam</hi> and <hi>Eve,</hi> till after their eating of the forbidden fruit, <hi>Gen.</hi> 3.7? What coverings had they (of the divine na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, glory and righteouſneſſe of God) in
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:121297:24"/>the day of their Creation? and could they ſee the want thereof before their eyes were opened?</p>
            <p>Let me further illuſtrate this thing thus; A child as ſoon as it is born, is ſaid to be an innocent, harmleſſe child,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.6.</note> free from the guilt or commiſſion of any ſin; is his na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture therefore pure, perfect, holy, heaven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and void of all inclinations to ſin? A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith of himſelf, that he was blameleſſe, as touching the righteouſneſſe of the Law, before his converſion: had he therefore an adequate righteouſneſſe, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very way agreeable and equall to the ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuality and holineſſe of the Law? Before the Law came he had little or no ſin, he was luſty and ſtrong in his fleſhly confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, he came into no misfortune or dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger of his life: but when the Law entred, his ſin abounded, his ſtrength weakned, his life withered and dyed. <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.20. <hi>Cap.</hi> 7.9. Sin was in his nature before, but not diſcovered till the Commandment came; it lay in him as a dead thing, under ground, out of ſight, and out of mind, it troubled him not, it was as a benummed or dead member, he was not ſenſible of it at all;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 7.8.</note>
               <hi>Without the Law, ſin is dead.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus the firſt <hi>Adam,</hi> He was created inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent (as they ſpeak) harmleſſe, &amp; voyd as yet of Doing any evill till the act of his diſobe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience in eating: but his condition, ſtate, or nature, in the day of his Creation, was not as pure, perfect, and holy as the Law of God: And the commandment came un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him to kill him, to make ſin abound and
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:121297:25"/>become exceeding ſinfull, that he might not think his preſent ſtate ſufficient,<note place="margin">Gen. <hi>1.31.</hi> Nakednes is want of divine righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes. Gen. <hi>3.11.</hi>
               </note> and content himſelf therewith, but dye unto that, and ſeek a better ſtate in Chriſt. He was naked and without the Wedding gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment at firſt, but was not aſhamed of his nakedneſſe; he was ſhewed, told, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinced of his nakednes by his preſumptu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous undertaking, of being more perfect in his own Way. And therefore God reaſons thus with him, <hi>Who told thee that thou waſt naked? haſt thou eaten, &amp;c?</hi> Thus <hi>Adam</hi> who was alive before the commandment came, is now killed by the Letter, and dies to that firſt life, his reſurrection to a better life being by the Promiſed Seed.</p>
            <p>Mr. Baker.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>But</hi> Adam <hi>in his Creation was not as</hi> Paul <hi>and all men elſe, or as children are now ſince the</hi> Fall, <hi>defiled with any originall polution.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, I doe not ſay that <hi>Adam</hi> was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taminated with any act of ſin, or unclean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe before his fall; yet this doth not prove him to be as exactly holy and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect as the Law, for if he had been ſo, how came he ſo crooked and contrary to the Law? The perfection of the Law conſiſts in perpetuity as well as in purity, and ſuch ſhould <hi>Adams</hi> ſtate have been if it had been equall to the Law. Yet,</p>
            <p>Secondly, If <hi>Adam</hi> had not in him the Principles and Seeds of ſin, how could he have tranſgreſſed and become a ſinner? for the ſpawn of wickedneſſe and evill in the Devill had not been enough to produce
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:121297:25"/>and propagate the prodigous off-ſpring of iniquity and ſin, unleſſe there had been ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table matter in <hi>Adams</hi> nature to mix with his ſerpentine ſuggeſtion and temptation. It is ſaid, <hi>Joh.</hi> 14.30.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 4.11.</note> That the <hi>Prince of the world came to Chriſt, and found nothing in him.</hi> He could never faſten any tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion on Chriſt, all his aſſaults could not prevail over him; had he found as little in the firſt <hi>Adam,</hi> as he did in the Second, there had been the like ſucceſſe, and no monſter of Miſery had been brought into the World.</p>
            <p>Mr. Baker.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Cauſe of the Cauſe, is the cauſe alſo of the effect, therfore if</hi> Adam <hi>had but the</hi> ſeeds <hi>and</hi> Principles <hi>of ſin in him, at his Creati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, though he were not actually a ſinner, yet you make God the author of ſin.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, What if I ſay, that God was the <hi>cauſe without which</hi> Adam <hi>had not fallen,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Cauſa ſine qua non. <hi>not</hi> cauſa impulſiva.</note> is there any hurt in that? God might have made <hi>Adam</hi> in ſuch an Immutable condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion that he could not have fallen, and then certainly you would have ſaid, God was the cauſe of his ſtanding.</p>
            <p>Secondly, A blind child is not in ſo good a condition as one that hath his eyes; yet the blindneſſe of the childe is neither his fault, nor his fathers,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luk.</hi> 3.38</note> though it be the cauſe of the childs ſtumbling and falling. <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam</hi> is called, The Son of God, this <hi>Adam</hi> was created blind, as to the ſpirituall un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding of divine things;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Io.</hi> 9.2, 3. <hi>Eph.</hi> 2.10.</note> yet neither did this man <hi>(Adam)</hi> uor (God) his parent
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:121297:26"/>ſin, in that he was born blind; but that the Workmanſhip of God in Chriſt might be manifeſted in him. It was not the fault, but the Wiſdome and pleaſure of God to make <hi>Adam</hi> ſo, that he might make way for the exaltation of his Holy child Jeſus, and the magnifying of the riches of his grace and love in Chriſt.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, Once more take it thus; A vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin not yet defloured, but retaining ſtill her chaſtity as in the day ſhe was born, you will not ſay, but this chaſte and pure vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin hath the Seeds and Principles of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pagation, and a deſire too of naturall iſſue; yet this Damoſell cannot be reproved of fornication as an harlot, nor hath ſhe ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned if ſhe marry and have children; ſhe is not to be accuſed of folly, unleſſe ſhe give up her ſelf to a ſtranger in an illegitimate and meretricious way. Who more chaſte and innocent then <hi>Adam?</hi> yet did he vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>olate that primitive and created purity, when he turned aſide to couple and cloſe with the allurements of the Serpent. He had not offended, if he had betrothed his ſoul to God in the Sacrament of the tree of life; yea, it had been more honor, hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſſe and ſafety, for him ſo to have done.</p>
            <p>The Devil is called the Father of murther and lies;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ioh.</hi> 8.44.</note> indeed he is the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of all that is evil; and therefore it is ſaid, 1 <hi>John</hi> 1.5.19. that the whole world (all that is of the word in oppoſition to God) lyeth in the <hi>Wicked one:</hi> every wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and ſinfull act lyeth in the loynes of the Devill, as the Father thereof; but except
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:121297:26"/>Satan had gendred with the lawfull heart of <hi>Adam,</hi> there had been noe ſuch bare born brat as ſin ever brought into the World,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iam.</hi> 1.13 15.</note> there was firſt luſt in <hi>Adam,</hi> which by the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jections of Satan, conceived and brought forth ſin;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 2.17</note> when he had compleatly finiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed his ſin in the actuall eating of the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidden fruit, then he dyed and not before, though he was mortall at firſt. Satan is the Father, mans heart the Mother of all e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill.</p>
            <p>Mr. Baker.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>But</hi> Adam <hi>was Spirituall at firſt, and therefore had not ſo much as any propenſity or inclination to ſin of himſelf, but what he was inticed unto by Satan: nor can it be ſaid, that he was blinde, as to the underſtanding of ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall things, in his created ſtate.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If <hi>Adam</hi> was ſpirituall or heavenly, in his created ſtate, what is the meaning, then of that in, 1 Cor. 15, 47. where it is ſaid that <hi>the firſt man is of the earth, earthy?</hi> And this is ſpoken of <hi>Adam</hi> before his fall, the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terials of which he was formed at firſt, were but duſt and earth; <hi>Gen.</hi> 2.7. yea, God, who beſt knowes his frame, mold, nature, and conſtitution of his being, called his name but <hi>Adam;</hi> man, or earth,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 5.2. 1 <hi>Per.</hi> 1.7 18.</note>
               <hi>In the day he was created:</hi> Or, as ſome will have it, <hi>red earth;</hi> which if it be meant of gold, to intimate the golden and excellent ſtate of <hi>Adam</hi> above other creatures, yet was he but red earth, or gold that periſheth; gold that could not make him rich to God: but the Saints gold which they have of the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:121297:27"/>
               <hi>Adam</hi> is tryed in the fire, and maketh rich indeed. <hi>Rev.</hi> 3.18.</p>
            <p>Again, the Apoſtle in diſtinguiſhing the two <hi>Adams,</hi> cals the one naturall, and the other ſpirituall, and concludeth the natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall to be before the ſpirituall; and that the Firſt man, in his greateſt excellency and higheſt perfection, viz. when he was a living Soul, was but naturall and earthy. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.44, 45, 46, 47. how you will prove <hi>Adam</hi> to be ſpirituall I cannot yet under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand.</p>
            <p>Mr. Baker.</p>
            <p>Adam <hi>was at firſt endowed with a ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all underſtanding, knowledge, righteouſneſſe, holineſſe, and every way like God, Immuta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility only excepted; for he knew the nature property, and uſe of every thing, and was a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to give names to every creature.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, That a naturall man might under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand the virtue, quality, cauſes, operati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and effects of naturall things; yet not diſcern the glory and excellency of ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naturall and divine things; theſe none knoweth, but the ſpirit of God. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.11. But,</p>
            <p>Secondly, If <hi>Adam</hi> were in all things like unto God, Immutability only except<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, where then was his Eternity, omniſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ency, omnipreſence, omnipotency, and the other Attributes of God?</p>
            <p>Mr. Baker.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>If</hi> Adam <hi>had not been in a ſpirituall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, how can he, be ſaid to fall, for his fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling preſuppoſeth him to be in a better and
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:121297:27"/>higher ſtate before, then he was after his fall?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To this I reply, by theſe inſtances,<note place="margin">Inſtan.</note> and ask you again:</p>
            <p>Firſt, Suppoſe a man to be clear and free from debt, one that owes nothing to any man, but hath no ſtock or ſubſtance of his own to make him to be accounted a rich man; yet he is a very rich man in compariſon of him that hath nothing, and oweth much beſides; that is ſo far in debt, he knowes not which way to get out. But may not he that had nothing (though ow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed nothing neither) run into debt, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come a poorer man then he was, when he neither had any thing, nor owed any thing. Some men are ſaid to be 1000 <abbr>l.</abbr> worſe then a groat; and as the Poet ſaid,</p>
            <q>
               <l>— Nil habet, &amp; tamen ille</l>
               <l>Perdidit, infoelix, totum nil —<note place="margin">Juven.</note>
               </l>
            </q>
            <q>
               <hi>He that hath nothing, may loſe even that whole no thing.</hi>
            </q>
            <p>Secondly, A civill honeſt man that hath but Morall principles and qualifications of righteouſneſſe, juſtice, equity, temperance, moderation and ſobriety; Such a man is more excellent and lovely, then a profane, rude and wicked man; yet may this man fall to lewd and vile courſes, though he ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver was a true Chriſtian and beleever of the Goſpel, doth his following of deviliſh practiſes now prove that he was a Saint be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore? doth his preſent walking, like an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidell, prove that once he had the faith of God?</p>
            <p>Thirdly, may not a pure virgin invitiate
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:121297:28"/>her primitive chaſtity, and become a noto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious ſtrumpet? yet you will not conclude, that therefore ſhe was lawfully married,-firſt to an honeſt man becauſe ſhe is nowfal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len from her firſt ſtate, and hath loſt her virginity.</p>
            <p>Firſt, <hi>Adam</hi> was created in a wealthy ſtate, in aſmuch as he was not all indebted to the Law, though he was not in poſſeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on or ſeiſed of the true riches of divine righteouſneſſe and glory. He had the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection of an earthy nature by Creation; but he had the participation of the divine nature by Promiſe. <hi>Gen.</hi> 3.15. 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.4.</p>
            <p>Secondly, He had all morall and naturall excellency belonging to his earthy and created ſtate. But was he ever the more endowed with the true treaſure of divine righteouſneſſe and holineſſe, for having ſhe image and ſuperſcription of the Heavenly King, upon no more but a piece of earth and clay? It muſt be more currant coyne of the pureſt ſilver and gold upon which the Kings picture muſt be ſtampt to make a man really rich in the poſſeſſion of it. It muſt be the divine nature, Jeſus Chriſt the ſecond <hi>Adam,</hi> the Heavenly man, that e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall word of God which paſſeth through the ſeven ſold diſpenſation of God to the world, in the ſeven dayes workes of his hands, as ſilver through a furnace; and is brought forth in ſpirituall purity,<note place="margin">Pſal.<hi>12.</hi>
               </note> the pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of the ſpirit and divine affection, this is that upon which God ſtamps his glory, and by which man is eternally happy.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, <hi>Adam</hi> had a virgin-like inn o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cency
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:121297:28"/>in his created ſtate; but not a Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trimoniall Union unto God: Or, at beſt, he was bound to God but with the bond of creation, which was as himfelf earthy; or the bond of the firſt Covenant, the Covenant of works; during which time he was barren &amp; unfruitfull in the knowledge of God, and in reſpect of any ſpiritual iſſue of divine com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort, immortall peace, joy unſpeakable and glorious, &amp;c.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 2.19.20.</note> But (in the ſecond <hi>Adam</hi>) God doth betroth his people to himſelf, in Mercy, Righteouſneſſe, and Truth, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by they ſhall <hi>KNOW</hi> the Lord: their Eſpouſals are for ever, and ſuch as where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by they have a true Spirituall knowledge of God. The Lord doth unite his people to himſelf in Chriſt, by a New Covenant,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eſ.</hi> 10.54</note> the Covenant of Grace; ſuch a Matrimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niall engagement that cannot admit of a divorce; ſuch ſweet enjoyments have they from Him, ſuch Conjugall and Spirituall Communion with Him, that they increaſe and multiply in their Joyes, Peace, Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort, Reſt, &amp;c, the barren is made fruitfull and a joyfull mother of many children. <hi>Eſ.</hi> 54.1, 2, 3, 4, 5. <hi>Pſ.</hi> 113.9.</p>
            <p>Mr. Baker.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>It it ſaid,</hi> Eccleſ. 7.29. <hi>that God made man <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pright, and what is that elſe but hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly and ſpirituall?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, in the creation (<hi>Gen.</hi> 1.) you ſhall find that God approved of his work (as he made it) as Good: and when he tooke a view of it altogether he concluded that it was very Good. <hi>Gen.</hi> 1.31. It is ſaid of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very thing as well as Man, that it was very
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:121297:29"/>good; will you therefore conclude that e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very thing that was made, is Heavenly and Spirituall?</p>
            <p>Secondly, Seeing there are ſo many Scriptures againſt you, to prove that <hi>Adam</hi> was but earthy and naturall, and not ſo much as one Scripture for you, to prove expreſly that he was ſpirituall; what ground have you to conclude ſo?</p>
            <p>Thirdly, Tis true, <hi>Adam</hi> was made Right, ſtrait, direct, even, plain, ſmooth, (or,<note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.40.41.</note> Upright, but not Righteous, Holy; or if Naturally and Morally, Righteous and Holy; yet not ſpiritually ſo. He had a rectitude <hi>ſuo genere,</hi> a purity and perfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in its kinde; anſwerable to his created being. The firſt <hi>Adam</hi> had (no more then a terreſtrial body, and a glory ſutable unto it: but the glory of Terreſtriall is one and the glory of Coeleſtiall is another. <hi>Adams</hi> glory was as farre inferior to the glory of Chriſt, as the Moone and Stars are below the Sun. The firſt <hi>Adams</hi> glory was to fall like the Stars, &amp; totally to be eclipſed, as the Moon may be. His hare, and even the mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtration of his Condemnation was Glory, how much rather then ſhall the Diſpenſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of righteouſneſſe by the ſecond <hi>Adam</hi> exceed in Glory? For even that glorious ſtare of <hi>Adam,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.10 11.</note> which was but meane and tranſitory, had no glory in reſpect of Chriſts glory, which excelleth and remai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth, as the Apoſtle diſcourſeth concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the tranſcending liberty of the Saints under the Diſpenſation of the Everlaſting Goſpel by the Spirit of Glory, above what
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:121297:29"/>the Jewes had under the beggarly Rudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of the Law.</p>
            <p>So far as the Naturall Jew can heighten himſelf towards Perfection by all the furni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture and accommodations of the worldly Sanctuary and the carnall Commandment, ſo far may he be a Poſt-repreſention (as I may ſo ſay) unto us of the firſt <hi>Adam.</hi> For as the firſt Temple was to be deſtroyed, and all the Worſhip and Services thereun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to to belonging to be aboliſhed; as the out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Jew was to be cut off, that the inward Jew might ſprowt forth; ſo may we there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by be put in mind, that we cannot enter into our Heavenly houſe, Chriſt Jeſus, that building of God; till this earthy houſe,<note place="margin">2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.1.</note> the Naturall ſtate of the firſt <hi>Adam</hi> be diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved. We take not poſſeſſion of our glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Manſion-houſe, Chriſt Jeſus, in the promiſed Seed, till our old mud-wall, earthy houſe of the firſt <hi>Adam</hi> be fallen about our ears, and become a ruinous heap; and God (as the Apoſtle ſaith of the Law and firſt Covenant) taketh away the firſt <hi>Adam,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.9 <hi>Ro.</hi> 8.20.</note> and ſubjecteth the firſt Creation to Vanity, that he may bring in the ſecond <hi>Adam,</hi> who eſtabliſheth and ſuſtaineth all things by the word of his power,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 1.3.7.19.</note> and with him a better hope, the hope of gaining a better ſtate in Chriſt, then was loſt by <hi>Adam.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>When the ſoul is once invironed with, and wrapped up in the glory of Chriſt Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus, it will tread and trample upon all the excellency of the earthy man.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rev.</hi> 12.1</note> It will not diſdain and ſcorn the ſublunary droſſe and dung of his fallen ſtate only, but it will
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:121297:30"/>alſo deſpiſe and contemne the very Lunary glory, the ſhining excellencies, the gold, ſilver, pearles and precious ſtones, the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection of the naturall and created ſtate.</p>
            <p>Mr Baker.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>But</hi> Adam <hi>was made in the likeneſſe and Image of God; and is not that ſpirituall?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, No <hi>like</hi> is the <hi>ſame: Adam</hi> was made in a <hi>ſimilitudinary</hi> and <hi>adumbraticall</hi> Righteouſneſſe and Holineſſe,<note place="margin">Nullum ſimile eſt idem. Eph. <hi>4.24.</hi>
               </note> but not in Righteouſneſſe and Holineſſe of <hi>Truth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, Hee was the ſhadow of the Subſtance, the Picture of the body: If a Painter draw the picture of a man never ſo exactly, will you ſay it is a living pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture?</p>
            <p>Thirdly, If the image of God in <hi>Adam</hi> be enough to make him ſpiritually holy and perfect, how will you defend Chriſt from being a ſinner?<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gal.</hi> 4.4. <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.3.</note> For it is ſaid, that God made his Son of a woman, under the Law, and ſent him in the likeneſſe of ſinfull fleſh: therefore Chriſt was really a ſinner: doth this follow? Yet this is your ratiocination, and the manner of your diſpute. <hi>Adam</hi> (you ſay) was made in the likeneſſe of God, who was ſpirituall holy, therefore <hi>Adam</hi> was ſo too: Why will not my argument hold as well as yours? And then it followes, that becauſe Chriſt was made in the likeneſſe of ſinfull fleſh, therefore hee had ſinfull fleſh really in him and about him, more then by imputation onely, if <hi>Adam</hi> had a ſpirituall holineſſe more then by imputation.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, Not to diſpute the Riſe and
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:121297:30"/>Original of the ſoul, whether it be, <hi>extradu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce annon,</hi> by propagation or infuſion? I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive <hi>Adam</hi> may be ſaid to be made in the Image of God in a two-fold conſiderati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Either as he was a living ſoule. In <hi>Luke</hi> the third, and verſe 38. <hi>Adam</hi> is cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the Son of God, as <hi>Enoch</hi> was the Son of <hi>Seth,</hi> and as <hi>Seth</hi> was the Son of <hi>Adam:</hi> for there the Genealogy of Chriſt after the fleſh, is carried backe and driven upward from <hi>Joſeph,</hi> and terminated in God.</p>
            <p>Miſtake not what I ſay, but reade it with a <hi>grain of ſalt.</hi> I doe not ſay, that <hi>Adam</hi> was the Son of God by naturall generation,<note place="margin">Caution.</note> ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to a groſſe, vulgar and carnall conſtruction, no more then any of the reſt were the ſons one of another by Creation; but as there was a continued derivation of life, by ſucceſſive propagation; the fountain of which life was in God.</p>
            <p>Now as God is ſaid to be the living God, and as <hi>Adam</hi> is ſaid to be a living ſoule; ſo <hi>Adam</hi> (as living, or having life) may bee ſaid to be in the Image of God. This ſeems to me to be the ſenſe and ſcope of that in <hi>Gen.</hi> 1.26. compared with <hi>Chap.</hi> 2.7. For that man which God would have to be made in his owne image; that man, even when he was compleated and perfectly finiſhed; the moſt that was ſaid of him is, that he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came a living ſoule. Here is the altitude and height of the firſt <hi>Adams</hi> perfections, as the Apoſtle takes meaſure of him: <hi>There is</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>a Naturall body, which is the firſt Adam,</hi> and was made a living ſoule, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi>
               <pb n="40" facs="tcp:121297:31"/>15.44, 45. A beaſt, <hi>quatenus Anmalis,</hi> as he is a living creature, is the image of a li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving man; yet this doth not prove a beaſt to be rationall; nor can you conclude that <hi>Adam</hi> was ſpirituall, becauſe he had a natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall life.</p>
            <p>If <hi>Adam</hi> had the image of God but only as he was a living ſoule,<note place="margin">Ob.</note> then every living creature, as Beaſts, Birds, &amp;c. may bee ſaid to have the image of God as well as man.</p>
            <p n="1">1. They might, indeed, be ſaid to have the image of God,<note place="margin">Sol.</note> if the Scripture did any where ſo ſpeake. But</p>
            <p n="2">2. God, who is <hi>Perfectiſſimus,</hi> moſt per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect, would attribute his image to the moſt perfect Creature, Man.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Beaſts, Birds, &amp;c. have the image of God in a large ſenſe, <hi>i. e.</hi> as they (with the whole creation) beare the ſtamp of the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall wiſedome and power of the God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head, <hi>Rom.</hi> l.20.</p>
            <p>Secondly, <hi>Adam</hi> may be ſaid to be made in the image of God, as he was a publique perſon, representing Chriſt; and ſo hee is ſaid to be the figure of him that was to come, <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.14. <hi>Adam</hi> was before Chriſt in priority of time and appearance in the fleſh; as the picture of a King ſent unto a forrain Princeſſe, may be ſaid to bee firſt (diſcovered and ſeene) in being in that Country;<note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.45.</note> and thus the Naturall is before the Spirituall. But in priority of cauſe Chriſt was before <hi>Adam,</hi> in the nature of his exi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtence; as the Efficient before the Effect, and as the body or ſubſtance muſt bee be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:121297:31"/>the picture which doth repreſent the body; and thus Chriſt is <hi>Alpha</hi> as well as <hi>Omega,</hi> the beginning and end, the firſt as well as the laſt, <hi>Rev.</hi> 22.13.</p>
            <p>God, who is Eſſentiall but One, hath a three-fold manifeſtation of himſelfe.</p>
            <p>Firſt, In the liveleſſe and darke ſhadow of the Law; in the Temple which had a graduall holineſſe, a place holy, more holy and holieſt of all. In the ſacrifice, &amp;c. The Law was but the ſhadow, not the Image, <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.1.</p>
            <p>Secondly, In the lively (though dimme and dull) ſemblance of man; in which thicke earth the divine majeſty had but a little weake ſplendour and luſter. Nor did the eternall power of the Godhead ſtampt on <hi>Adam,</hi> make him divine, or of an eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall power like it ſelfe: Neither did the image of Gods ſpirituall Righteouſneſſe and Holineſſe in man make him ſpiritually righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous and holy. The Kings image ſtampt upon a piece of Clay, doth not make the Clay to be Gold, nor living Clay.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, In the living ſubſtance, Chriſt Jeſus, who is the brightneſſe of his Fathers glory, and the very character of his being,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Joh.</hi> 1.17.</note>
               <hi>Heb.</hi> 1.3. This, and this onely is that Son, that onely begotten Son, that came out of the boſome of the Father, which alone can (ſpiritually) declare and make known God as he is a Spirit, and bring forth abundance of Grace, Righteouſneſſe, Life and Immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tality to light, <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.17, 18. 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.10. Immortality comes by Chriſt; <hi>Adam</hi> was not Immortall, nor Spirituall.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="42" facs="tcp:121297:32"/>
               <hi>Abraham</hi> had two ſonnes, one after the fleſh, the other by promiſe; the elder was after the fleſh, and was not to inherite with the younger, which was by promiſe, <hi>Gal.</hi> 4.22, 23, 30.</p>
            <p>Our <hi>Abraham</hi> alſo, God, the High and Holy One, the Eternall Father, hath two Sonnes, one after the fleſh (as I may ſay) the naturall or firſt <hi>Adam;</hi> the other after the ſpirit, Chriſt, the promiſed ſeed. The elder Son, or firſt <hi>Adam,</hi> had not the Inhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritance of Righteouſneſſe, Life and Glory ſetled upon him; but Chriſt, the ſecond <hi>Adam,</hi> was appointed heire of all things. <hi>Iſhmael,</hi> though he was the firſt-borne of <hi>Abraham,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 1.2.</note> had no poſſeſſion of <hi>Abrahams</hi> heritage; the promiſed Land was not en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>talyd on him, neither was he counted for the ſeed. And why ſhould we thinke that <hi>Adam,</hi> though he was the firſt-born of God by creation, had an hereditary right to hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, righteouſneſſe or <hi>(Divine)</hi> holineſſe, ſeeing he is not counted for the Seed. The inheritance of true divine righteouſnes, &amp;c is conferred and confirmed on Chriſt, the ſpirituall <hi>Iſaac,</hi> and thoſe that are his, <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.14, 16, 29.</p>
            <p>Mr Baker.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>We are exhorted,</hi> Eph. 4.24. <hi>to put on the new man, which after God is created in righteouſneſſe and true holineſſe. And</hi> Col. 3.10. <hi>the Apoſtle tels them, That they had put on the new man, which is renewed after the image of him that created him. What elſe doth the Apoſtle there meane</hi> (by the new man) <hi>but the firſt</hi> Adam <hi>recovered from his fall,
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:121297:32"/>and reduced to his priſtine and primitive ſtate?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. Looke upon thoſe Scriptures againe, and tell me whether the Apoſtle ſpeaks of putting on the new man, or the old?</p>
            <p>Now if you will have the new man there to be meant of the firſt <hi>Adam,</hi> then you con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>found the two <hi>Adams:</hi> For the firſt <hi>Adam,</hi> (in his pure naturall, as well as in his lap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed eſtate) and thoſe that are of his race, are every where in Scripture, that I know, di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinguiſhed by the name of <hi>(Old Adam)</hi> from Chriſt, and thoſe that are his ſeed, who (in oppoſition to the firſt <hi>Adam</hi>) is called the New Man.</p>
            <p n="2">2. It is ſaid (<hi>Col.</hi> 3.20.) that that New man which we are to put on, is renewed (in Knowledge) after the image of, &amp;c. Which cannot be underſtood of the firſt <hi>Adam:</hi> for me never reade that knowledge is cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the image of God in the firſt <hi>Adam.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There is therefore a two-fold image of God.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Of Life: In this <hi>Adam</hi> was formed, when he was made a living ſoule. This life, and the righteouſneſſe, perfection and glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry thereof, though it be but naturall, is ſo precious unto man, that skin for skin, and all that he hath will he give for it.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 2.7. <hi>Job.</hi> 2.4.</note> It is the maſter-peice of Satans temptations, and the laſt plot uſually, that he hath on man to ſet upon him as he did on Chriſt, <hi>Mat.</hi> 4.8, 9. The Devill will carry a man to the higheſt pitch of the firſt <hi>Adam,</hi> as to the top of an exceeding high mountaine (for <hi>Adams</hi>
               <pb n="44" facs="tcp:121297:33"/>created ſtate was farre more exceedingly high, then any preſent, naturall and world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly condition of man now) and there ſhew him all the dominion that <hi>Adam</hi> had over all that earthly creation, and what a glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous ſtate he was in: And then this old ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent tempteth and entiſeth man to looke upon this golden ball of vanity, and accept of it, tels him he ſhall be (As) God. But the ſpirituall man, Chriſt, diſcernes and foreſees the danger, eſpies the ſerpent un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the hearbe, knowes there is death in the apple, and therefore deſpiſeth all the pompous vanity of the firſt creation. When Satan, by deſpaire, cannot breake a mans necke from the fall of <hi>Adam,</hi> he will bring him to the brinke and brow of his created ſtate, and from thence endeavour to call him downe (as the Jewes did to Chriſt) and make him runne headlong to his flattering ruine.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luk.</hi> 4.29. <hi>V.</hi> 5, 6.</note> When the Devill cannot drive a man away from God by the corrupt <hi>Adam,</hi> hee will draw him to himſelfe by the pure <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam,</hi> and there hold him as a cloſe priſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, in fetters of Gold, as he did before in ſhackles of Iron. The Kingdome, Power, Glory of this creation, is delivered to the God of this world. The Serpent tooke a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way mans excellency and glory; the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent offers it him again upon tearms Sure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly that cannot be worth the taking up, which the Devill proffers, and if Satan have dominion, and be Lord over mans ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, to give and take at his pleaſure, I can hardly be perſwaded that it is ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall: The enemy of man hath laid his
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:121297:33"/>earthy honour in the duſt,<note place="margin">Sic tranſit gloria, mundi.</note> and trod his life to the ground.</p>
            <p>I wonder that we ſhould ſo much dote upon the painted Beauty of man! Tis a ſign our eyes are weak, and that we are dim-ſighted, not able to behold the Beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of holineſſe in God Beſides, what hope is there for us to recover <hi>Adams</hi> State? For if there was a totall privation (as doubtles there was of <hi>Adams</hi> life,<note place="margin">a privati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>one ad ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitum non datur re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſus.</note> there can be no more regreſſe to it. <hi>Adam</hi> is not ſaid to ſwou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d or faint, but to die in the day he did eat: not the death of the body, for he lived many hundred yeers after; but the death of that State, to which he was not to return again. And therefore we are bid to mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tify the old man, not labour to recover him to his health and ſtrength. Nor will it ſerve the turn to ſay, that as we dyed in <hi>Adam,</hi> ſo we are made alive by Chriſt; as though our reviving by Chriſt were no more then a reſtitution to the life or the firſt <hi>Adam:</hi> for our life which we have by Chriſt, is by reſurrection not by regreſſion; not a retur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning to the ſame life, but a rayſing to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother life.</p>
            <p>There is alſo the image of God as it con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſts in knowledge, <hi>Col.</hi> 3.10. And this i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage I do not find attributed to <hi>Adam;</hi> but is peculiarly appropriared to Chriſt,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eſ.</hi> 11.2.3 <hi>Col.</hi> 2.3.</note> and thoſe that are his. Not <hi>Adam,</hi> but Chriſt hath the ſpirit of Wiſdome, Knowledge, and a quick underſtanding; and in Chriſt not in <hi>Adam,</hi> are hid all the Treaſures of Wiſdome and knowledge. If <hi>Adam</hi> had had a true ſpirituall and Divine knowledge
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:121297:34"/>of God and Chriſt, in the tree of Life , he had been immortall and could not have dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, for the ſeed of that Knowledge is E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall, and ſo is the fruit too. <hi>Iohn</hi> 17.3. and 1 <hi>Iohn</hi> 3.9.</p>
            <p>Every man is brutiſh in his knowledge, ſaith the Prophet, <hi>Jer.</hi> 10.14. yea, he is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come brutiſh by his knowledge. <hi>Ier.</hi> 51.17. Not only in his low, baſe and fallen ſtate; but even in his high and Honorable ſtate; Man <hi>(in Honour)</hi> is but as a beaſt, for want of underſtanding.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſ.</hi> 49.20.</note> Man <hi>(Adam)</hi> had ſo little knowledge in his excellency, glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, Honour, that he became as the <hi>Behe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moth, as the multitude of earthy beaſts. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam</hi> was as a <hi>Behemoth,</hi> or the multitude of earthy beaſts.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Either in that he had as little true and ſpiritual knowledge of the Myſtery of God and Chriſt as all the whole multitude or a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny particular beaſt of the field.</p>
            <p>Secondly, Or as he was a publike Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, and had in him all poſterities and ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerations of men, who in him and with Him are altogether out of the way, brutiſh in their knowledge, and naturally as Igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant of God, and his Righteouſneſſe as the beaſts that periſh.</p>
            <p>The Wiſdom of the fleſh is the Serpent, that moſt ſubtill beaſt in the field of this earthy Creation,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 3.</note> which ſteales into the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>radiſe of Mans natural excellency and glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, and there circumventeth him with the enchantments and ſnares of Death. Curſed Creature! let it be thrown flat on its belly and let its food be for ever nothing but the
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:121297:34"/>duſty vanities of the ground that is under foot and trampled upon (like that lofty City, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 26.5, 6.) by the feet of the poor and the ſteps of the needy, ſcorned, deſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, ſleighted Saints, let it eat and live on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly upon the fooliſh, frothy, fleſhly prayſes of the Natural Man; let its meat be nothing elſe but the carnall earthy righteouſneſſe of that fickle, frayl, inconſtant, unſtanle, tranſient ſtate of the firſt <hi>Adam.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And yet, O the depth of the Wiſdome and works of the Lord! how unſearchable is his underſtanding, counſell, purpoſe! his wayes are in the waters, and the beames of his chambers are there; He hath a ſweet and ſecret entertainment for his people beneath and within the fluctuations, oeſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ations, ragings, foamings, confuſions of the ſea and waters of this creation; his thoughts towards his Saints are very deep, a foole cannot fathom them, an unwiſe man cannot finde them out; He contriveth the way of mans happineſſe, to lye within the Gates of his ruin and deſtruction , that he which lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth his life may finde it. Mans wiſdom of the fleſh, his own luſt draweth and driveth him to the ditch of Death,<note place="margin">Periiſſem niſi peri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſſem.</note>
               <hi>Ian.</hi> 1.14, 15. this like the Serpent, doth ſtab man to the heart by a glance upon the rib, <hi>Gen.</hi> 2.22 &amp; <hi>Ch</hi> 3.1, &amp;c. to ſay that mans wiſdom was or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained for a trap &amp; ſnare of death unto him cannot be born, and will not be granted by all; but to ſay that God did, and doth ſo order and diſpoſe it to that end, can be denyed by none: the Lord can over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>whelm the Egyptian fleſh with its chariots
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:121297:35"/>and Horſes, humane Wiſdome and carnall reaſon, in the ſelf ſame ſea that he carrieth the true ſpiritual Iſrael into ſhe Holy land. The principles of mans mortality are ſeat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed within Himſelf,<note place="margin">Nemo loe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditur niſi aſe ipſo.</note> but the cauſe of his health and life is in, and from the Lord. <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 13.9. The earthy Wiſdom and knowledge of man conſiſts in, and is converſant about doing that which is evill. <hi>Jer.</hi> 4.22. thus was <hi>Adams</hi> knowledge imployed and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved; and will any one ſay, this was the image of God?</p>
            <p n="3">3. But perhaps you lay hold on the word <hi>(renewed)</hi> Col. 3.10. and think that it importeth and implyeth as much as Reſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution, (and no more) of Man to <hi>Adams firſt ſtate.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, If you look well upon that Scripture, you ſhall find that the Apoſtle ſpeakes of that New Man in whom there is neither Greek nor Jew, &amp;c. ver. 11. which the Apoſtle more plainly affirmes to be Chriſt. <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.28.</p>
            <p n="2">2. But if you do keep to that word, Rene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wed, it wil ſtand you but in little ſtead. If a man pull down his old houſe and renew it, or build another New houſe;<note place="margin">2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.1.</note> you will not ſay that new houſe is the ſame that the old was.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Hag.</hi> 2.9.</note> The <hi>firſt</hi> Temple was a <hi>ſtately ſtructure</hi> although it had not a commenſurate and adoequite ſplendour and magnificence to the ſecond, which did far exceed the <hi>firſt in luſter</hi> and <hi>glory.</hi> The earthy Jeruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem was an holy City, it had a holineſſe of attribution and dedication, nor of inherent, eſſentiall or true divine holineſſe, nor was
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:121297:35"/>it the ſame with that Jeruſalem, which is above. And that holy City,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gal.</hi> 4.25.26.</note> the earthy Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem you ſhall ſind given up to be trod under foot of the Gentiles.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rev.</hi> 11.21.</note>
               <hi>Rev.</hi> 11.2. and <hi>Chap.</hi> 21.2. you have the holy City the new Jeruſalem coming down from God out of heaven; but differing from the former, for this had no Temple,<note place="margin">22.</note> nor need of Sun, or Moon to ſhine in it, <hi>ver.</hi> 22, 23. &amp; <hi>Ch.</hi> 22.1, 2, 3, 4, 5. there is the Heavenly paradiſe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed, as the Anti-type of the earthy, but with this difference, <hi>i.e.</hi> of Immutability and perpetuity. The curſe entred into <hi>Adams</hi> paradiſe and blaſted all his happineſſe, he abode not there as a Lord for ever; but here is no curſe, and they that have <hi>(holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe)</hi> the name of God in their fore heads, ſhall reigne for ever and ever, Ver 3, 4, 5. The firſt Paradiſe, Holy City, and Temple, were types of the heavenly, but not Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly. The holy City of mans earthy and created ſtate and Paradiſe, God ſubjected unto vanity and corruption, and gave it o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver to be trod under foot thereby, and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terward cauſeth righteouſneſſe to looke down from heaven.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſ.</hi> 85.11.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Mr. Baker.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>If</hi> Adam <hi>was any way defective and not made ſpirituall in his Creation then it argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth inſufficiency and want of wiſdom in God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This objection was none of your own, but borrowed of a neighbouring preacher, as I was informed by one, after our confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence was ended, and we parted. But ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing I have met with it (though at ſecond
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:121297:36"/>hand) I ſhall take notice of it, and return this anſwer thereunto.</p>
            <p>It was the will of God, not any want of Wiſdom in God, to make the <hi>firſt Adam</hi> but earthy and Naturall.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſa.</hi> 135.56.</note> He is, to give ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count to none but himſelf. He is above all Gods, and may do what pleaſeth Himſelfe in heaven and in earth. If his pleaſure was to make an earthy <hi>Adam</hi> as well as a ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall, and yet would finde fault too with that earthy <hi>Adam;</hi> nevertheleſſe, who ſhall reply to him,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 9.19.20.</note> or ask a reaſon of him , why he did ſo?</p>
            <p>Was it not one and the ſame piece of clay in the hand of God, of which he made Man &amp; beaſt? And did it imply want of ſkil in God becauſe he did not make the bruit beaſt a reasonable Creature as well as man? tis at the potters pleaſure to form his veſſel as he will, whether for honour or diſhonor.</p>
            <p>In a great houſe (ſaith the Apoſtle) there are, veſſels, not only of gold and ſilver, but alſo of wood &amp; earth,<note place="margin">2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.20</note> ſome to honour and ſome to diſhonour. It doth not argue want of ſkill in the workman, nor want of wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom in the maſter of the houſe, in that e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very veſſel is not of gold. But what if God, willing to ſhew his wrath, and to make his pleaſure known, daſhed in pieces the veſſel of diſhonour, that earthen veſſel of the <hi>firſt Adam</hi> and his created State, ſitted to ruin and deſtruction; and that he might make known the riches of his glory on the veſſels of Mercy which he had afore prepared (in Chriſt, not in <hi>Adam</hi>) unto glory: what if the wiſdom of God (which ordereth all
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:121297:36"/>things) diſpoſed ſo of theſe things, have you any thing to ſay againſt it? what if God would make way for the magnifying of his heavenly riches of grace in Chriſt, by undermining the earthy treaſure of man in the firſt <hi>Adam.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is rather a prudent plot, then an im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>provident folly; and the admiration of di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Wiſedome, no detraction from it, to make darkneſſe firſt, and then command light to ſhine out of it.</p>
            <p>The earthy man in the beginning of his created ſtate was without forme, and void of divine righteouſneſſe, and then darkneſſe was upon the face of the deepe things of God: and when God by his ſpirit in the Eternall Word; Chriſt Jeſus had (as now he doth) brought forth light, (<hi>Gen.</hi> 1.2. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.10. <hi>John</hi> 1.3, 4, 5.) yet he did, and ſtill doth divide and diſtinguiſh be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene the light and darkneſſe, <hi>Gen.</hi> 1.4, 5. 1 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 5.5. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.40, 44, 47, 47.</p>
            <p>Light and Darkneſſe, Earth and Heaven, the firſt and ſecond <hi>Adam,</hi> and their righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe are not all one, yet God did not want art and skill when he made all theſe, though he did not make Earth Heaven, nor the firſt <hi>Adams</hi> righteouſneſſe ſpirituall and heavenly.</p>
            <p>If you exclaim thus againſt me for error and hereſy when I tell you but of the earthy man, how would you cry out blaſphemy if you ſhould be told all that may be ſaid of the heavenly man, Chriſt Jeſus himſelfe, in reſpect of the fleſhly knowledge of him? If you tremble and ſtagger thus at an earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quake,
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:121297:37"/>what perplexity would you be in, if you ſhould &amp; ſee hear the heavens paſſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way with a great noiſe, &amp; the elements melt with fervent heate? If you cannot endure to ſee the earth and the workes therein to be burnt up,<note place="margin">2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.10.12.</note> how will you be able to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold the diſſolution of the heavens by fire, and the melting of the elements by a ſcorching heate? If you cannot beare the ruine of the earthy <hi>Adam,</hi> but are ſo moved at the ſhaking of the foundation of his ſtate;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>He.</hi> 12.27.</note> how then will you undergoe the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution of the heavenly <hi>Adam,</hi> when hee ſhall reſigne his Kingdome,<note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.24.28. <hi>Gal.</hi> 4.3.9.</note> Glory, Domini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and State to a higher Diſpenſation? When the Apoſtle wrote of theſe things, <hi>viz:</hi> theſe weake and beggarly Elements which were to paſſe away, and not to returne againe; theſe things, theſe Elements were hard to be nnderſtood.<note place="margin">2 <hi>Pe.</hi> 3.16</note> And becauſe you diſcovered your weakneſſe to beare the one, I ſhall forbeare to burthen you with the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                  <desc> _____ </desc>
               </gap> Mr Baker.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>You goe againſt the judgment of all Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vines; contrary to the opinion of Orthodox, learned and godly men. Anſwer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. I reſpect, honour and reverence god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe in every man, in all men; Yet am I not to regulate, bound or modulate my faith by the wiſedome, notion or meaſure of any mans apprehenſions: no, though the moſt godly and moſt learned among men. And therefore we are not to enquire what this or that mans thought, opinion or judgment is, of ſuch or ſuch a point, but what the Scripture doth ſay, determine or
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:121297:37"/>conclude of this or that particular.</p>
            <p>Our faith is not to ſtand in the wiſedome of men;<note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.5 1 <hi>Th.</hi> 2.13</note> this were to lay the foundation upon ſand. Nor are we to receive the Word it ſelfe in the word of man, but as it is, in truth, the word of God.</p>
            <p>Truth is not Truth becauſe man ſaith it, but becauſe it is ſo in it ſelfe; neither is it ſo to any man, till it come unto him in the power and demonſtration of the ſpirit. The Scriptures themſelves were given, not by tradition of men, but by inſpiration of God. Scripture is not Scripture to a man, till it come to him in the ſame ſpirit by which it was dictated at firſt.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Whereas you urge the opinion of godly and learned men, as contrary to mine, and they preachers too; among whom you made mention of Mr <hi>Ball,</hi> in his Cate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiſme; tis more then I know, or care to enquire what he ſaith in this matter: but be it granted that he (and others too) are contrary-minded: What then? I could produce many that are on my ſide, and ſoe oppoſe godly and learned men againſt your godly and learned; yet then there would be but man againſt man.</p>
            <p>Let the matter be brought to the Teſt, &amp; let the Touch-ſtone diſtinguiſh between the gold and the droſſe: <hi>to the Law and to the Teſtimony;</hi> If the Scripture caſt the truth on your ſide, I will ſubſcribe. I cannot bee ſatisfied, becauſe ſome of your Authors are in print: the publiſhing of an opinion in print wil not make it Orthodox.</p>
            <p n="3">3. By what Councell or Synod am I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>victed
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:121297:38"/>and condemned for an Heretike? Produce it if you can. But, if you caſt mee by your owne ſingle vote, will it not ſavour of too much arrogance and pride, to aſcribe unto your ſelfe a definitive ſentence, and power to determine what is truth, and what is errour? And may not I, upon the ſame ground, and by the rule of your owne pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe, raile upon and defame you, as you have ſerved me? Or if you take in others to joyne with you, (or rather proſtitute and give up your faith to their judgement, as you ſeemed to doe) may not you and they be miſtaken as well as I and thoſe that are of my judgement.</p>
            <p>Yea, grant that what I hold to bee con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned and exploded for hereſy, I am not therefore to diſſert and relinquiſh my opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, becauſe a Convention of men doth eliminate, exterminate and eject it for an errour: And you (who are led ſo much by the determinations of men) will confeſſe what I ſay to be true, and when you ſee my authority, you will not cenſure mee of ſingularity.</p>
            <p>It is the ſaying of one, eminent for godli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and for learning inferiour,<note place="margin">Mr. Rey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nolds in Expoſion Pſal. <hi>110.</hi> in fallor</note> I thinke, to few or none, that we are not to build our faith upon the authority of men, or counſels, whether Papall, Epiſcopall or Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nodicall; I have not his Booke by me, theſe are his words, I am ſure. So that if this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent deliberate and long-conſidering Synod ſhould put it, as an Article of their Faith, into their New Creed, and enjoyne all to ſubſcribe to it under paine of <hi>Anathema,</hi>
               <pb n="45" facs="tcp:121297:38"/>viz: <hi>that the firſt</hi> Adam <hi>was made ſpiritually holy and righteous:</hi> Yet I am not bound to believe it: The reſults of humane counſell are not infallible; and one <hi>Paphnutius</hi> may be in the right, when the whole coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell is in the wrong.</p>
            <p>Mr Baker.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>I cannot yet be perſwaded, that what you ſay, is true; though you may ſeeme to make any thing good by your Schollarſhip.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. Tis not the worke of man, but of God, to perſwade the heart.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Act.</hi> 16.14</note>
               <hi>Paul</hi> may plant in the ear of <hi>Lydia,</hi> but God muſt give the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe in her heart. <hi>Paul,</hi> &amp; other men, may ſow the divine ſeed in the letter thereof, in the ſenſe of hearing and the rationall fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulty of the underſtanding; but God muſt breake and pierce thoſe clods of earth, fleſh and naturall reaſon; he muſt throughly o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen the carnall heart, before there can be any encreaſe or fruit ſpringing up in the ſpirit, before there can be any improve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of that ſeed unto the knowledge of the Divine Myſtery. And therefore, as the King ſaid to the woman in another caſe,<note place="margin">2 <hi>Ki.</hi> 6 27</note> If the Lord helpe you not (to underſtand and receive the myſtery of the two <hi>Adams</hi>) whence ſhall I helpe or perſwade you?</p>
            <p n="2">2. I ſee you are very prone to miſtake, and too ready to run into extreames: for whereas, at firſt, you did me too much wrong, now (in a Complement) you would doe me too much right. If you ask all that knew me both in the Country and Univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity, there is none that can ſay I ever had
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:121297:39"/>ſo much learning as might give the deno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination of a Schollar.</p>
            <p n="3">3. But how doe you entangle your ſelfe? For you confeſſed (and I did believe you without an oath) that you had but little learning your ſelfe, and yet you affirmed with much confidence, that learning was neceſſary (indeed you did not ſay abſolute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly neceſſary) for the underſtanding of di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Truth.</p>
            <p>Immediate revelations, you ſaid, are not to be expected now adayes:<note place="margin">Neceſſari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um eſt ſine quo res non poſſit ſe habere.</note> How then can you judge betweene truth and falſhood? or ſoe peremptorily conclude me to be in an errour, ſeeing you acknowledge your igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance in humane learning, which, you ſay, is neceſſary to the better underſtanding of ſpirituall things? If you rely on other mens opinion, and <hi>jurare in verba,</hi> reſolve to be of their judgement: your fairh will ſtand in the wiſedome of men, not in the power of God: and why may not one man (the wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſt man) deceive you as well as another? If humane learning, and the wiſedome of this world be ſo neceſſary, what then is the meaning of that in <hi>Mat.</hi> 11.25. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.18, &amp;c. and <hi>Chap.</hi> 2. It may be ſaid of learned as well as of great men, that they are not alwaies wiſe.</p>
            <p>Concerning humane learning, I gave you my judgement at our meeting: I look upon it as the flouriſhes of fleſh, an handſome faſhion, a neate dreſſe, a comely ornament of the creature: It is as <hi>ſtudds</hi> and <hi>barbes,</hi> the externall furniture and trimming of the outward man; It is <hi>Phallera ad populum</hi>
               <pb n="57" facs="tcp:121297:39"/>Gay and gaudy trappings, to make an ugly Jade or a dull Cart-horſe looke like a good mettled and well-bred Beaſt: a block-hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded Dunce in the myſtery of God and the Goſpell, in this Canonicall habit, may paſſe, <hi>Vervecum in patria,</hi> amongſt a generation of Idiots, and ſilly animals, for a moſt Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verend, Grave and Orthodox Divine. It ſerves to ſcratch the pruriginous humour of the ſenſuall part and principle, to tickle the itching eare of a nice, quaint and curi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous man: Yet good ſtill in its kinde, and to be allowed in its place and ſpheare, ſo long as it moves regularly and in order; but but when once it begins to uſurpe and ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rannize, it is no rebellion to oppoſe and diſclaime it.</p>
            <p>Humane learning is of an Heroicke Race, well deſcended, of noble bloud and birth in natures family; but a moſt profuſe and prodigall Steward in the myſtery of God,<note place="margin">Maxima quaeque domus ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vis eſt plena ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perbis.</note> not fit to be entruſted with the Heavenly Treaſure. It will ever be aſpiring to prece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dency, like a new raiſd ſervant, or ſome proud encroaching Gentleman in a great Houſe, who hath nothing to ſubſiſt by, but the courteſy and bounty of the Maſter of the Houſe, and is but as his Almeſ-man; yet if he can but inſinuatingly collogue and play the Paraſite with one that beares rule; he will be ready to domineere over the home-born Children and the naturall heire of the Family. Such baſe and degenerate ſpirits may be found (as too many preſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents, to the ſhame of our Nation) here in <hi>England,</hi> who can but, <hi>cliena jactare,</hi> boaſt
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:121297:40"/>of other mens worth, and do <hi>aliena vivere quadra,</hi> live on other mens wealth, who live and lurke like Dorres and Drones in a Common-wealth, without care and calling and have no cloake or covering for their ſloth and idleneſſe,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.5. <hi>Act.</hi> 22.3.</note> but that they are Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlemen: whereas a truly generous Nature loves to be active and induſtrious, and hates a ſupine and ſottiſh ſluggiſhnes as the moſt ſordid and odious kind of life.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Cha.</hi> 18.3. <hi>&amp;</hi> 20.34.</note> Paul was as well born and bred as moſt men; yet he did not ſcorne, or think it any diſparage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to him or his family, to earn his li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving <hi>manu ac tela,</hi> with the labour of his hands, when he might have lived upon the ſweat of other mens browes, in reſpect of his own bodily pains, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 9.12.15.</p>
            <p>If humane art and Wiſdome can but once flatter the favour and ſteal into the friendſhip of the Naturall Will, the carnal reaſon and underſtanding; it will ſoon in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veigle the heart, and alienate the affections of a man from the holy ſeed, the Spirit, Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt the true heir of ſalvation.</p>
            <p>I deny not but that godlineſſe and the myſtery of God may be beſtowed upon men of learning, but I ſay alſo that it is not committed to the learning of men, ſo as that, thereby they ſhould be more qualified for the diſpenſation of the everlaſting Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel. But if mans Wiſdom be ſet in the chaire and called <hi>Rabbi,</hi> Father, Maſter, or Doctor; if it be any wayes aſcribed unto either for generation or education of the new Man, I deteſt and abhorre it, <hi>as the vileſt off ſcorning in the world,</hi> and as a
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:121297:40"/>thing ſo bad as that I want a word to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe my utter hatred of it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>You will ask me how I could have had the Scriptures without learning and the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of the Tongues to tranſlate them?</hi>
               <note place="margin">Queſt.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Humane learning will ſerve for tranſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the letter,<note place="margin">Anſw.</note> and render the grammati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call ſenſe and conſtruction of Scripture, and this is all. But how did the Saints doe before there was any Scripture?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>But are not you your ſelf better qualified by your learning for the exerciſe of your mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtry?</hi>
               <note place="margin">Queſt.</note>
            </p>
            <p>All the learning I had at <hi>Oxford,</hi> I layd out and improved in oppoſing the truth.<note place="margin">Anſw.</note> I cannot ſay, that the little learning I once had, did advantage or further me one jot in the knowledge of God, nor doe I think my ſelf any whit the fitter to be a miniſter becauſe of the repute and notion of ſchol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar-ſhip which ſome vainly harbor of me. And to deal plainly and ingeniouſly with you, when I was under the teaching of men I got more from ſimple countrey people, huſband-men, weavers, &amp;c. about <hi>Brink-worth, Southwick,</hi> and thoſe parts in <hi>Wilt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhire,</hi> then ever I did, or yet have by books and preachers.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>If you make no more account of learning, but ſo much deſpiſe and undervalue it,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Queſt.</note>
               <hi>why doe you make any uſe of it?</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1 The dregs and reliques in a veſſell will remain a while and retain ſome cent and favour of the liquor that was it it,<note place="margin">Anſw.</note> after the liquor is drawn out. <hi>Quo ſemel eſt imbuta recens,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <pb n="60" facs="tcp:121297:41"/>
2. There be ſome men that ſometime may, &amp; ſometime may not be anſwered accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to their cavils &amp; propoſals: <hi>Pro.</hi> 26.4.5. I know ſome will caſt this proverb in my diſh, <hi>The Fox diſlikes the grapes becauſe he cannot reach them,</hi> &amp; <hi>Science hath no enemy but Ignorance.</hi> I may as wel retort, <hi>Nemo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gis Rhombum ſtupet quam</hi> Catullus coecus, <hi>who more bold then blind Bayard? who more blind then thoſe that ſee?</hi> Joh 9.40.41.</p>
            <p n="3">3. I would ſtrike off <hi>Goliah's</hi> head with his own ſword, if I could. If I could but enter them, I would ſmite the ſtrong holds and garriſons of the <hi>Philiſtins</hi> with their own weapons, and turn the mouth of their own Canon againſt them, to batter down all their bulwarks. If my breeding had been at Court, and all the learning of the <hi>Egyptians</hi> had been beſtowed upon me, I would diſdain to be called <hi>the Son of Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raohs daughter.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>He.</hi> 11.24</note> Had I the art and ſkill of <hi>Archimedes;</hi> yea, all the Wiſdome of the World and could thereby make ſuch an engine as would remove the abominati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of deſolation out of the holy place, I would not fayl to doe it, and make ſuch a ſcourge as ſhould whip the Simonaical mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants (who think that the qualifications of a Miniſter are to be purchaſed with the coſt of education at ſome Univerſity) out of the Temple of the Lord, it ſhould have no place in the Worſhip of God, though it may be allowed in the Worſhippers. The tooles of man will polute the Altar of God.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ex.</hi> 20.25</note>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. That may be uſed for reprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:121297:41"/>of mens enormities, which is not uſed by way of edification in Truth and Godli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe. <hi>Paul</hi> (after he had diſclaim'd and renounced the Wiſdome and learning of man) took occaſion to lay open and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove the vitious courſes of the heathen from their own Poets, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.33. <hi>Tit.</hi> 1.12. But the reformation from thoſe lewd and wicked manners he aſcribes to the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpenſation of the Goſpel, <hi>Tit.</hi> 2.11.12. The law it ſelf may curſe and kil, it cannot cure; it may reprove &amp; convince, it cannot make alive, quicken and convert unto God.</p>
            <p n="5">5. Jt was lawfull for the Iſraelites to take the jewels of ſilver and gold from the <hi>Egy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptians,</hi> that they might ſpoyle the <hi>Egy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptians.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Exo.</hi> 32.4.</note> Exod. 3, 22.12.35.36. Yet ſee what a ſnare theſe jewels became unto Iſrael, when their very Prieſt <hi>Aaron</hi> himſelf had converted them to an idolatrous uſe in the Molten Calfe. Now they became ſo loath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome and odious that <hi>Moſes</hi> burnt thoſe je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wels to aſhes. The children of Iſrael could not carry ſo filthy and abominable thing into the holy and promiſed land of Canaan.</p>
            <p>Humane learning, Naturall parts, &amp;c. are the <hi>Egyptian</hi> jewels of this world, which the Iſrael of God, the Saints themſelves may borrow and wear as ear-rings, they wil ſerve to adorn a mans diſcourſe and hang as a jewell in the ear of the Auditor. But ſuch is the madneſſe of out-ſide Jewes, Letter-Chriſtians, and formall profeſſors that they muſt ſee their God; their God muſt goe before them, they will not be content with the Making-God, but they muſt have a
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:121297:42"/>made Gods, Gods-made in a viſible and ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible ſhape that they may ſee their God before them: But bleſſed are they that have not ſeen and yet have beleeved. And ſuch is the raſhneſſe, folly, and ſimplicity of Men-prieſts, who ſeek the favour and prayſe of men, more then of God; that to pleaſe a giddy, and head ſtrong Multitude they will comply and give them what reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, Worſhip, or God they call for. If the vulgar popularity cry up Preſbytery, that ſhall be eſtabliſhed for a time, and but for a time, for the tyde may turn; Indepen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dency may come in faſhion, and then very like if that be deſired, it will not be deny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. The common people muſt be ſatisfied or elſe tythes, dues, and worldly mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>renance will fail. Now the ear-rings are called for; gifts, parrs, abilities, indow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, theſe qualifications of nature with a little of the Spirit (which may well e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough be left out too, were it not for faſhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and better ſound ſake in diſcourſe) will make up a compleat Miniſter. How many having but paſſed through the ſire of an A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cademicall education, a ſleight: and formall examination, and a powerleſſe, weak, and liveleſſe Ordination, have come forth mol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten Calves, and many a ſilly ſoul hath dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced about them as their Ghoſtly-Fathers, demy-ſaviours, and petty-Gods When hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane parts and learning are mixt in the worſhip of God to ſpecificate, modifie, or denominate it, then it becomes Idolatrous. This calfe we carry not into Canaan, any otherwiſe then as Iſrael having drunke of
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:121297:42"/>the water into which the powder was thrown, <hi>Exod.</hi> 32.20. might be ſaid to car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry the Calf into <hi>Canaan</hi> as it is obſert in Chriſt; it is not ſeen nor named under the diſpenſation of the Spirit: Mans Wiſdome and parts may beautifie the things of man, but no way adorn the things of God; what need you overlay gold with copper?</p>
            <p>Mr. Baker.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Is any man (think you) ſo ſimple to make a god of learning, or to look, upon it as any thing, any farther then as it is ſanctifyed by the Spirit?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. Where hath the Spirit ſanctified it to the qualification of a Miniſter in all the Scripture?</p>
            <p n="2">2. Do you think that the Iſraelites were ſo ſtupidly ignorant as to take the Molten Calfe for the Immortal God? yet when they would have a viſible repreſentation of the inviſible Being, and change the Glory of the Incorruptible into the image of cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptible man, beaſts, &amp;c. God gave them up (as well as the Gentiles) to dote upon and follow that which was not God, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 81.12. <hi>&amp; Job.</hi> 19.20. <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.21, 23, 24. When God ſpeaks to man there is no ſimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litude of Himſelf (in the wiſdom, parts, and excellency of Man, or the Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of the firſt <hi>Adam</hi>) to be ſeen. The ambition and induſtry of the Creature is to bring down the Creator into the lower re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion of ſenſible appearances, to cloath and compaſſe the incomprehenſible Diety and Myſtery of the Lord Jeſus, and the glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:121297:43"/>Goſpel of God in viſible formes and the Wiſdome of the fleſh; and when men have made a God like themſelves, and faſhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned a Religion and Worſhip after the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vention of their own fancies, they are rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to cry out with the <hi>Lyſtrians</hi> in <hi>Lycao<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nia, God is come down to us in the likeneſſe of man.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Act.</hi> 14.11</note> The longeſt, largeſt and wideſt form, Order, and Ordination of man is too ſhort ſtrait, and narrow to circumſcribe and li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit the bleſſed teaching of the infinite Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of the Holy one of Iſrael. He hath lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning enough that can ſpeak a word in due ſeaſon to him that is weary. <hi>Eſa.</hi> 50.4.</p>
            <p>Mr. Baker.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>You go about to bring in a boundleſſe and unlimited</hi> Independency, <hi>to give liberty to any that doth but pretend unto the Spirit to preach; you open a door to let into the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtry every</hi> mechanicall <hi>fellow, tinker, ſhoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maker</hi> (<hi>ſuch an one as is at</hi> Nottingham) <hi>weaver, amp;c. And if ſuch as theſe may be permitted to vent the frothy humors of their ſhallow braines, under pretence of being qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lified by the Spirit for the Miniſteriall functi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and office, then we are to have a goodly, wiſe, and learned miniſtry indeed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. Did the Biſhops (or will the Preſby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters) keep all Dolts, Drones, and Dunſes out of the miniſtry?</p>
            <p n="2">2. Why may not <hi>(even)</hi> an exorbitant Epiſcopacy and a boundleſſe <hi>Independency.</hi> (as you call it) be as good as a groundles, proud, tyrannicall and domineering Preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bytery? I ſtand no more for an eſtabliſhed
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:121297:43"/>form of <hi>Independency,</hi> then for a ſetled go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment by Preſbytery, &amp; for neither any more then for a reformed Epiſcopacy.<note place="margin">2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.16</note> to let this paſſe, for though once I had this fleſhly knowledge of men, yet henceforth know I neither men nor C. ſo any more, but rather ſeek to know as I am known in the Spirit.</p>
            <p n="3">3. As for the ſhoemaker at <hi>Nottingham,</hi> which you ſpake of, and other mechanicall men,<note place="margin">R. J.</note> (as they are termed) I know nothing to the contrary, but that they may ſit in the chair as wel as many of your great <hi>Rabbies.</hi> I gave you inſtances of divers, who, having performed the prieſts office in his Canoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal veſtments, have been ſaluted for currant divines both by Parliament men, and Synod men too; &amp; they no <hi>Independents</hi> neither.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Jerome</hi> ſpeaks of it as the glory, not the ſhame, and makes it the commendation, not the diſhonour of thoſe times, that the Scripture was familiarly known to taylers, ſemſters, delvers, ſhoemakers, &amp;c. why ſhould not we rejoyce of <hi>all the Lords peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple were Prophets,</hi> and to ſee the Spirit pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red out upon all fleſh?</p>
            <p n="4">I approve not any more then you do of precipitate, raſh, ignorant fools, that run be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they are ſent into the miniſtry. If any pretend to have the qualification of the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, &amp; hath it not, reject that man as a Phari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaical hypocrite: but if any have the gift take heed you throw not water in his face to quench the ſpirit of propheſy in him; If God bid any one go about his work, let no man diſcourage or forbid him to do it; Chriſt wil not alow his own beloved diſciple to forbid nother to do his work, although he hath
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:121297:44"/>not the ſame formall and verball commiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and doth not walk in the ſame external call and ceremony of Diſcipleſhip with the other. He that never had hands of Men layd on him,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luk.</hi> 9.49 50.</note> may <hi>caſt out as many Divels</hi> and convert as many ſoules, as he that goes out with never ſo many ſpels and charms of fleſhly Ordinations and Inſtitutions of Men.</p>
            <p>Mr. Baker.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>In your diſcourſe concerning the blind man,</hi> Joh. 9. <hi>you ſaid, that when eyes were fully o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pened we never read that afterward he pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to receive his ſight, whereby yon ſeemed to glance at ſuch a ſtate of Perfection here, in which there ſhould be no need of Prayers, but a continuall rendring of prayſes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. I ſay againe, that mercies received ſhould cauſe returnes of prayſes, one of the ten lepers returned to Chriſt: what to do? to pray unto him to be cleanſed,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luk.</hi> 17.15, 16.</note> or to give him thanks for being cleanſed? when you have beſtowed your almes, do you expect the beggar ſhould lie at your gate begging, or go away thankfull?</p>
            <p n="2">2. I know there is ſuch a ſtate of Perfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction attainable here, wherein there ſhall be continuall prayſes. Is not death, ſorrow, crying, curſe and payn removed, and all teares wiped away in the New <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem, Rev.</hi> 21.4.22.3. and what will there be left then, but matter of inceſſant prayſes? this is the condition which ſome, I do not ſay all, are in; do I therefore deny the ſpirit of ſupplication to thoſe that are
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:121297:44"/>in doubts, wants, ſtraits, bondage, and have not yet the pokeſſion of their deſires and hopes? Do I hold prayer uſeleſſe and need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe in every condition?</p>
            <p>Mr. Baker.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>You give me cauſe to think ſo; for when you preached laſt year at</hi> Derby <hi>you ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver made confeſſion of ſin, nor prayer for the pardon of it before your ſermon, though it were on a faſt day, whereby I gueſſe you are againſt faſting and humiliation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. If I had followed the form and pat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tern of your private ſpirit, I ſhould have given you content; but I am not bound to take my dictates from man.</p>
            <p n="2">2. You ſay that I did not (then) confeſſe nor pray for the pardon of ſin; no, though it were on the faſt day: hence you inferre, that I deny confeſſion and prayer for par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don of ſin to be lawfull. I do not well re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member what I ſayd ſo long ſince: But let me follow you in your reaſoning; When I met with Mr. <hi>Baker,</hi> I heard him plead much for prayer, but little or nothing for prayſes. <hi>Ergo,</hi> Mr. <hi>Baker</hi> denyes prayſing of God to be lawfull. I pay you in your own coyn, you muſt not refuſe or diſlike it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Mat.</hi> 11.25. Chriſt gave thanks to his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, but did not then pray for any thing we find there; <hi>ergo</hi> he never prayed at all, as holding it unlawfull ſo to do. I did not confeſſe, &amp;c. when you heard me, therfore I ſay that none ought ſo to do, or I never did or may do ſo my ſelf. I never had ſo much Logick to underſtand your argument.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="68" facs="tcp:121297:45"/>
And whereas you conclude alſo that I am againſt the duty of humiliation, I reply as before; If you had the diſpoſing of my ſpirit, I ſhould pleaſe you.</p>
            <p n="3">3. I forbid not the Diſciples of <hi>John</hi> and the <hi>Phariſees</hi> to faſt and pray often.</p>
            <p n="4">4. I grant that the children of the bride<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chamber may (and cannot do otherwiſe but) mourn when the Bridegroom is ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 9.14.15.</note> muſt they therefore faſt and weep and mourn when he is preſent?</p>
            <p n="5">5. Dayes of humiliation are ordained by men now, and obſerved by ſuch as are ſubject to men, in the manner, notion, and nature that they are injoyned. Men may commend the obſervation of dayes, they cannot command the ſanctification of them; they may propoſe the form and time of faſting, they cannot diſpoſe the frame and affections of the heart. It may be ſeaſonable for one man to pray, when it is more ſutable for another to be ſinging of Pſalmes. Nationall communion, ſeldome or never hath its Union in the Spirit. If Principalityes or Powers cannot ſeparate us form the love of God in Chriſt Jeſus;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ro.</hi> 8.38.</note> if rulers and Magiſtrates of this preſent world cannot eſtrange or take away the Bride<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>groom from the Saints, they cannot im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe upon them the bewayling of his ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence. Civill powers may command the corps, they are not captains of the conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence.</p>
            <p>I hear what will be objected: <hi>Did not the Jewes</hi> (ſay ſome) <hi>obſerve thoſe dayes and times which were appointed for faſting,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ob.</note>
               <hi>feaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:121297:45"/>&amp;c. and enjoyned by their Kings and Civill Magiſtrates, who were but men.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. They did ſo; ſo may the Jewes doe ſtill: let thoſe that are under the diſpenſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Old Teſtament walke in it. If the civill Magiſtrate make decrees and ſend forth his edicts, let them be obeyd by thoſe that are bound by conſcience thereunto, but let not conſcience be bound or enfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced by them. The outward Jew hath no King but <hi>Caeſar,</hi> the inward none but Chriſt: let both theſe exerciſe their reſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctive power and juriſdiction, and all ſtrife will ceaſe.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The whole Paedagogye and Policy of the Jewes, people and all were an externall and typicall Ceremony, which yet had in them and contained an internall and Anti-typi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call equity and morality. The Law in the letter, was by <hi>Moſes,</hi> the Law in the Spirit is in Chriſt: The children of Iſrael would needs have a King over them, like other Nations, whoſe Kings exerciſed Lordſhip over them, and were called benefactors; the the children alſo of Iſrael in the Spirit have (Chriſt) their King over them, the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment is upon his ſhoulders; He reignes over the Houſe of <hi>Jacob,</hi> He exerciſeth lordſhip over the conſcience, yet ſo, as that he may well be called a Benefactor: He breaketh the earthen formes, cuſtomes, Principles, Religion, Worſhip, &amp;c. in pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, with his iron rod (of the Spirit) like a potters veſſel, but withall doth erect and ſet up ſuch a divine and ſpirituall diſcipline that (He may wel be called a Gracious Lord,
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:121297:46"/>becauſe of the Word of Truth, Meekneſſe, and Righteouſneſſe, the ſcepter of Grace, Mercy and Love with which he ruleth; and the terrible things which his right hand doth in ſhooting his ſharp arrows into the heart of his enemies,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 45.</note> luſt, ſin, fleſh and cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption, He it is that can kill and cure, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy and make alive, confound and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort, make ſad or rejoyce, command a feaſt or faſt. Tis no good way of arguing to make up the concluſions of one ſcience from the Principles and Proemiſes of ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther:<note place="margin">Tranſitus a genere ad genus.</note> That which was done under the law, and in a type or ceremony will not hold under the Goſpel in the verball and litteral ſenſe of it: what things the Law ſaith, it ſaith to them that are under it; and what things the Spirit ſaith, it ſaith to them that that are led by it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>But we are commanded by the Apoſtle,</hi> Rom. 12.15. <hi>to weep with thoſe that weepe, and to mourn with thoſe that mourn, even now under the New Teſtament, was not this preſent faſt injoyned for</hi> Irelands <hi>ſad conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion whoſe miſeries yet continue?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Tis all confeſt and granted, but doth that imply a conſtant and continued obſervati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of a ſet and fixed time?<note place="margin">Sol.</note> Is any man ſure to have his heart in a fit and ſutable temper for faſting againſt the laſt <hi>Wedneſday</hi> in every moneth? are not the preparati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the heart, and anſwer of the tongue (wholly) from the Lord?<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pro.</hi> 16.1.</note> God may di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpoſe one man for ſinging at the very ſelf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſame inſtant of time, that another is ſtirred up to prayer. If the Lord give a cheerful
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:121297:46"/>heart to offer up prayſe and thankſgivings, will it be convenient, at that time to ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice the oblation of a dul and penſive ſpirit received from the injunctions of Man? He that hath his heart diſpoſ'd to mourn, let him mourn: who doth forbid him? and he that hath his ſpirit drawn forth to rejoycing let him rejoyce: who ought to hinder or judge him? One man may have his heart in a frame fit to keepe the monthly faſt, another man may be more fit to faſt at another time; yet this man may truly bewail and condole the mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeries and afflictions of <hi>Ireland and England</hi> as well as the other, and ſo fulfill the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand or exhortation rather of the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle, in weeping with thoſe that weep. He that doth faſt upon <hi>Monday</hi> or <hi>Tueſday,</hi> without an Ordinance of Parliament, may be as tauly humbled as he than keepes the <hi>Wedneſday-faſt,</hi> and more truly it may be: for thoſe duties which flow from the more immediate ſuggeſtions of God unto the ſoul are more ſound and cordiall then thoſe that are irritated and provoked by the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtigations of mans precepts. He that ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerveth a day, let him do it to the Lord; and he that obſerveth not a day, let him not be judged and condemned by men. Read the 14. Chap. to the <hi>Romanes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Mr. Baker,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Hitherto I have contended for truth, not for tryumph, I ſhall now let fall the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcourſe and leave it before the judge. In all that I have here ſet down, the moſt High
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:121297:47"/>God, my conſcience and yours can beare me witneſſe that in nothing you are wron<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged by me. Your name is prefixt to no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but what (for matter and ſubſtance) was ſpoken and aſſerted by you; when you juſtified your charge and carriage, and maintained, and defended your ſlanderous reports and defamation of me, you provo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked me to a ſharp reply, and to tel you that you had done very uncivilly, diſhoneſtly and moſt unchriſtianly, at which you took great ſnuffe, but let others judge whether I had not cauſe. I told you alſo that I might as well rayl againſt you behind your back, as you had done by me, but that I ſcorned ſuch baſeneſſe, and thought it not ſit to render rayling for rayling; this I ſayd to your face, and more then this (nor ſo much) you ſhall never prove that I ſpake behind your back. Nor did I intend to put theſe paſſages and proceedings be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween us in print, when I told you at our parting, that I reſolved to require a more publike account from you, ſuppoſing that a fair, free, and friendly debate of the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter among ſome friends in theſe parts might have been ſufficient to have taken up, and compoſed the difference. But when I heard (about three weeks ſince) that you had di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vulged and blazed it abroad into other parts, I thought it as convenient, juſt and reaſonable for me to make the vindication of truth as publike as you have made the imputation of an error.</p>
            <p>Your practiſe in this kinde, I doubt, hath been a bad Preſident to others; for two
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:121297:47"/>or three Pariſh-preachers hereabout have ſince accuſed me of poyſoning the people at <hi>Hener</hi> with error &amp; falſe doctrine:<note place="margin">Mr. Cr. of Br. Mr. H. of Weſ.</note> but by that time their covetous practiſes, common tipling, exceſſive gaming, &amp;c. are fully examined and layd open to the world they will appeare to be ſuch <hi>Antinomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Independents,</hi> ſuch <hi>Independent Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nomians</hi> as will make them altogether incapable of the office of a Biſhop. I cannot charge you of being active with them, but I ſuſpect and fear that you have been exemplary to them.</p>
            <p>Sir, Before I take my leave, I ſhall (as a friend) ſuggeſt one thing unto you, <hi>i. e.</hi> When the ſhadow of the firſt <hi>Adams</hi> excellency is ſo bigge and long upon the earth, it is too cleare a ſigne that the Day-ſtarre is very low and lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle in the Horriſon of mans heart; the ſecond <hi>Adam;</hi> that Heavenly Sunne of Divine Righteouſneſſe, Chriſt Jeſus, is declining and drawing near the ſolſtice of <hi>Capricorne,</hi> He is in a weak and low appearance, known too much after the fleſh, when the glorious light and day of the bleſſed and eternall Spirit is ſo ſhort and Dark.</p>
            <p>I have not endeavoured to ſhame you, but to ſift out the truth, and to give you and others occaſion to exerciſe your thoughts upon the myſtery of God and man, Chriſt and <hi>Adam.</hi> When your me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditations are ripe and perfected, let pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like profit be made of them. I have layd down nothing but my experiences, and
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:121297:48"/>what I have heard and ſeen, as I have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived the Lord Jeſus, and been taught the truth in Him. I have no more to ſay to you, or any man elſe, but,</p>
            <q>
               <l>— Si quid noviſti rectius iſtis,</l>
               <l>Candidus imperti; ſi non, his utere mecum.</l>
            </q>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:121297:48"/>
            <opener>
               <salute>Mr. Calvert,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <hi>I</hi> Hear it is reported by ſome that I am ſad, melancholike, ſick, and keep my chamber; by ſome that I am dead; by o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers that I am mad, and out of my wits, ſince I was with the Generall at <hi>Wind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſor.</hi> This (as I am informed) is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported by my friends. When Chriſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan to ſet forward his Fathers work, his friends thought he was beſide himſelfe, <hi>Mar. 3.21.</hi> and when <hi>Paul</hi> carried on that work he fell under the ſame cenſure, <hi>Act. 26.24.</hi> and what of all that, ſo long as it is to God? <hi>2 Cor. 5.13.</hi> I bleſſe the Lord of whom I have obtained mercy, and from whom I have received the ſpirit of power, of love, and of a ſound minde, <hi>2 Tim. 1.7.</hi> I enjoy that which is better then my ſelf, or the life it ſelf, which maketh me to ſcorn and overlooke the reports and reproaches of men. Here it is ſaid of me, (as of others heretofore) that I am a peſtilent fellow, a mover of
<pb facs="tcp:121297:49" rendition="simple:additions"/>ſedition, one that poyſoneth and decei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth the people, &amp;c. I am not aſhamed of the bleſſed and glorious Goſpell of my Lord Jeſus Chriſt, nor afraid of the bonds of the Goſpel, or of perſecution, for the Spirituall, Divine, and Heavenly Righteouſneſſe-ſake of God. I have therefore ſent you theſe few ſheets of pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, deſiring you to make them publike to the view of all men. I am</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your aſſured friend</hi> Henry Pinnell.</signed> 
               <dateline>
                  <hi>Riſly in Derby-ſhire</hi> 
                  <date>
                     <hi>Octob. 14. 1648.</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:121297:49"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
